So hello everyone.
안녕하세요 여러분.
Welcome to lecture 7.
7강에 오신 것을 환영합니다.
I also wanted to go over some clarifications from last time.
지난 시간의 몇 가지 설명을 다시 하고 싶습니다.
So when I gave lecture last time,
지난 강의에서 제가
there were two ed posts that I think were good that you all
좋다고 생각한 두 개의 게시물이 있었는데, 여러분이 확인하고
might want to check out.
싶어 할 것 같습니다.
But in case you haven't seen it, I'll
아직 보지 못하셨다면,
just go through it really quickly.
제가 빠르게 설명하겠습니다.
I think when describing dropout, how
드롭아웃을 설명할 때, 테스트 시간에
to scale probabilities at test time during lecture,
확률을 조정하는 방법에 대해
there was a bit of confusion.
약간 혼란이 있었던 것 같습니다.
Basically, what I said in the slide had a mismatch.
기본적으로, 슬라이드에서 제가 말한 내용이 일치하지 않았습니다.
So in each forward pass for dropout
드롭아웃의 각 순전파에서 우리는 이
we have this hyperparameter p, which is either
하이퍼파라미터 p를 가지고 있는데,
the amount of neurons you're dropping out
이는 드롭아웃하는 뉴런의
or it's the amount of neurons that you're
양이거나 사용하는 드롭아웃
keeping depending on which implementation
구현에 따라 유지하는
dropout you're using.
뉴런의 양입니다.
Generally they do.
일반적으로 그렇습니다.
It's the number of the ones you drop out.
드롭아웃하는 뉴런의 수입니다.
So in most libraries that's what p means.
대부분의 라이브러리에서 p는 그렇게 의미합니다.
But the basic idea is that at test time,
하지만 기본 아이디어는 테스트
you want the expected output to be the same as at training time.
시간에 기대 출력이 훈련 시간과 같아야 한다는 것입니다.
So this means that if you dropped 25% of your activations
즉, 훈련 시간에 25%의 활성화를 드롭아웃했다면,
during training time, at test time, you would scale by 0.75,
테스트 시간에는 0.75로 스케일링하여 기대
so that the expected output is the same.
출력이 같아야 합니다.
And so I think there was a bit of confusion
그래서 이 슬라이드에서
because in this slide the implementation uses p
구현이 단위를 활성 상태로 유지하는 확률로
as the probability of keeping a unit active.
p를 사용하기 때문에 약간의 혼란이 있었던 것 같습니다.
So a bit of a mismatch there.
조금의 불일치가 있었습니다.
Just to clarify.
명확히 하기 위해서입니다.
There was also a question in class from last time about how
지난 수업에서 정규화가 어떻게 유용할 수 있는지에
normalization can be useful.
대한 질문이 있었습니다.
And maybe resolve the issues that
그리고 잘못 초기화된
arise when you have weights that are initialized incorrectly.
가중치로 인해 발생하는 문제를 해결할 수 있습니다.
But we have this choice setting where we have 2D inputs
하지만 우리는 모델에 2D 입력이 있고 ReLU를
to our model, and a two layer neural network with ReLU.
사용하는 2층 신경망이 있는 설정을 가지고 있습니다.
It's outputting basically this quadrant function.
기본적으로 이 사분면 함수를 출력합니다.
So if the point lies in the top right, it'll output 1 or 2
그래서 점이 오른쪽 상단에 있으면, 점이 위치한
or 3 or 4, depending on which quadrant the point lies in.
사분면에 따라 1, 2, 3 또는 4를 출력합니다.
And we plot the different training losses and test losses
우리는 지난 시간에 논의한 Kaiming 초기화를
for good initialization using the Kaiming initialization
사용한 좋은 초기화와 표준 편차가 너무 높은 나쁜
we discussed last time and bad initialization
초기화에 대한 다양한 훈련 손실과
where the standard deviation is too high.
테스트 손실을 플로팅합니다.
And the blue plot here represents bad,
여기에서 파란색 플롯은 나쁜 초기화를 나타내고, 초록색은
and the green represents bad initialization with LayerNorm.
LayerNorm을 사용한 나쁜 초기화를 나타냅니다.
So you can see it actually does resolve a lot of the issues.
그래서 실제로 많은 문제를 해결하는 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
But to get the best performance you still
하지만 최상의 성능을 얻으려면
need good weight initialization, which
여전히 좋은 가중치 초기화가
are the two lines afterwards.
필요하며, 이는 이후의 두 선입니다.
So you can go dive in.
그래서 깊이 들어가 볼 수 있습니다.
And also, whether or not LayerNorm help
또한 LayerNorm이 도움이
depends on the problem.
되는지는 문제에 따라 다릅니다.
So in this quadrant I, you can imagine that you don't need
이 사분면 I에서는 각 점의 정확한 2D
to know the exact 2D position of each point.
위치를 알 필요가 없다고 상상할 수 있습니다.
So LayerNorm was actually helping.
그래서 LayerNorm이 실제로 도움이 되었습니다.
But for some of the other functions that are in the code,
하지만 코드에 있는 다른 함수들 중
you can check out, where you need
일부는 정확한 좌표를 알아야
to know the exact coordinate in order to get the right output,
올바른 출력을 얻을 수 있으며,
LayerNorm actually hurts performance
LayerNorm은 평균을
because you lose some information
빼고 표준 편차로
about the exact spatial location of your input
나누는 과정에서 입력의 정확한
when you're doing the subtraction of the mean
공간 위치에 대한 정보를 잃기
and dividing by the standard deviation.
때문에 성능을 저하시킵니다.
So just some notes here.
그래서 여기 몇 가지 메모가 있습니다.
Basically at a high level, it does help with the issue,
기본적으로 높은 수준에서 문제를 해결하는 데 도움이 되지만, 여전히
but a gap remains.
간극이 존재합니다.
So you can't get by this weight initialization issue
그래서 단순한 정규화로는 이 가중치 초기화
with just normalization.
문제를 해결할 수 없습니다.
And as I mentioned, it may not always
그리고 제가 언급했듯이, 모델링하려는
make sense depending on what you're trying to model.
것에 따라 항상 의미가 있을지는 아닙니다.
So I think just to recap also from last time,
그래서 지난 시간에 대해 요약하자면,
we've been mainly talking about these sort of vanilla, standard,
지금까지 주로 이러한 일반적인 비순환
non-recurrent neural networks so far.
신경망에 대해 이야기해왔습니다.
So this is a fixed size input and a fixed size output.
이것은 고정 크기 입력과 고정 크기 출력을 가지고 있습니다.
You have this one time setup where you set your activation
여기에서 활성화 함수를 설정하는 한 번의
functions.
설정이 있습니다.
You do data pre-processing according
이미지와 이미지 채널에 대해
to some fixed mean and standard deviation for the images,
고정된 평균과 표준 편차에 따라 데이터 전처리를
the image channels.
수행합니다.
You have your weight initialization
사용하는 가중치 초기화
and normalization functions that you use,
및 정규화 함수와
as well as transfer learning.
전이 학습이 있습니다.
So if you pre-train on one data set, like ImageNet
하나의 데이터 세트, 예를 들어 ImageNet이나 다른 대규모
or some other large scale internet data set,
인터넷 데이터 세트에서 사전 훈련을 하면,
you can get better results if you initialize your weights
가중치를 해당 값으로 초기화할 경우 더 나은 결과를
to those values.
얻을 수 있습니다.
We also talked about training dynamics,
훈련 동역학에 대해서도
how you can babysit the learning process in choosing
이야기했으며, 좋은 학습률을
a good learning rate, how you want
선택하고 다양한
to update your different hyperparameters,
하이퍼파라미터를 업데이트하는 방법,
and also how to optimize those based on the validation
그리고 검증 성능 및 테스트
performance as well as test time augmentation
시간 증강을 기반으로 최적화하는
to improve performance further.
방법에 대해 논의했습니다.
So a really good tool for points 2 and 3
여기서 2번과 3번에 대한 정말 좋은 도구는 제가
here is something I use in basically all my projects called
모든 프로젝트에서 사용하는 'weights and biases'라는
weights and biases.
것입니다.
So you might find this useful.
이것이 유용할 수 있습니다.
It's a really neat way that you can essentially
다양한 하이퍼파라미터로 서로 다른 실행을
look at different-- you set different runs
설정할 수 있는 정말
with different hyperparameters.
멋진 방법입니다.
In this case, they show a dropout column here.
이 경우, 여기에서 드롭아웃 열을 보여줍니다.
So these are all the different values of dropout.
이것들은 드롭아웃의 다양한 값들입니다.
The color coding is really nice.
색상 코딩이 정말 좋습니다.
So you can see that generally the lower values of dropout
일반적으로 드롭아웃의 낮은 값이 더 높은
will achieve higher accuracy.
정확도를 달성하는 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
And so you can visualize these different validation--
그래서 검증 세트 성능에 따라 이러한 다양한
sorry, these different hyperparameters
하이퍼파라미터를
based on validation set performance.
시각화할 수 있습니다.
And you can see based on many runs
여러 번의 실행을 통해 어떤 하이퍼파라미터가 가장 잘
get an idea of which hyperparameters work best.
작동하는지 알 수 있습니다.
So I always use this.
저는 항상 이것을 사용합니다.
I think it's great.
정말 좋다고 생각합니다.
Especially if you have the compute where you can just
특히 성능을 더 개선하기 위해 반복적으로
run something over and over again
실행할 수 있는
to improve performance more, this
컴퓨팅 자원이 있다면, 이는
is a really neat way of visualizing it.
시각화하는 정말 멋진 방법입니다.
I think they do it well.
그들은 잘하고 있다고 생각합니다.
There are other tools like TensorBoard.
TensorBoard와 같은 다른 도구들도 있습니다.
But this is personally the one that I like.
하지만 개인적으로 제가 좋아하는 것은 이것입니다.
OK, so for the rest of lecture today,
좋습니다, 오늘 강의의 나머지 부분에서는
we'll be discussing sequence modeling.
시퀀스 모델링에 대해 논의할 것입니다.
So this is, in contrast to a fixed sized input
이것은 모델에 대한 고정 크기 입력과 대조적으로,
as input to our model, what if we have
가변 길이의
a sequence of variable length.
시퀀스가 있을 경우입니다.
And also, we'll be discussing what
또한 변환기 시대 이전에
are the simple neural networks that people
사람들이 사용하는 간단한
use before the era of transformers,
신경망에 대해서도 논의할 것입니다.
which mainly consists of RNNs and some variants of RNNs.
주로 RNN과 그 변형으로 구성됩니다.
And then I'll also relate in one slide
그리고 RNN이 실제로
how RNNs actually are similar to a lot of, and inspire a lot of,
많은 현대 언어 모델, 즉 상태 공간 모델에 어떻게 유사하고
the modern type of language models
영감을 주는지를 한 슬라이드에서
that you see called state space models.
설명하겠습니다.
So you might have heard of Mamba.
Mamba에 대해 들어본 적이 있을 것입니다.
There's some other ones too that we'll talk about in the slide,
슬라이드에서 이야기할 다른 것들도 있지만, 기본
but the basic idea is the key concepts from RNNs
아이디어는 RNN의 핵심 개념이 오늘날에도 여전히
are still being used today.
사용되고 있다는 것입니다.
They're not just used in the past,
그들은 과거에만 사용된
and they have a lot of nice advantages
것이 아니며,
over transformers that will go into.
변환기보다 많은 장점을 가지고 있습니다.
Cool, so to specifically formulate this sequence modeling
좋습니다, 이 시퀀스 모델링 작업을 구체적으로 공식화하기
task, you can imagine, we have a vanilla neural network
위해, 우리는 고정 크기 입력에서 고정 크기
where we have one fixed size input to one fixed size
출력으로 가는 일반적인 신경망을 상상할 수
output, which is what we've discussed in the course so far.
있습니다. 이는 지금까지 강의에서 논의한 내용입니다.
In contrast, you could have a one to many sequence modeling
대조적으로, 하나의 입력에 대해 여러 개의 출력을 생성하는 시퀀스 모델링 작업을 가질 수
task.
있습니다.
So here we still have a fixed size input like say an image,
여기서 우리는 여전히 이미지와 같은 고정 크기 입력을 가지고
but we want to output a sequence of variable length.
있지만, 가변 길이의 시퀀스를 출력하고자 합니다.
So one common example is image captioning.
일반적인 예로는 이미지 캡셔닝이 있습니다.
So we input an image and we want to output
이미지를 입력하고 언어를 모델링하거나
a sequence of words or characters
인코딩하는 방식에
or however you're modeling the language or encoding it,
따라 단어 또는 문자 시퀀스를 출력하고자 하며,
but the goal is to have a variable length caption
목표는 이미지에서 발생하는 상황에
output for what's happening in the image.
대한 가변 길이의 캡션 출력을 갖는 것입니다.
You could also have a many to one sequence modeling task.
여러 개의 입력에 대해 하나의 출력을 생성하는 시퀀스 모델링 작업도 가능합니다.
So here we could imagine our inputs are, say, a video
여기서 우리는 입력이 비디오라고 가정하고, 이 비디오가
and we're trying to classify what is this a video of.
무엇인지 분류하려고 합니다.
So we give it a sequence of video frames.
비디오 프레임의 시퀀스를 제공합니다.
And the output is one single class label similar to the image
출력은 이미지 분류 사례와 유사하게 하나의 클래스
classification case.
레이블입니다.
But now we have multiple frames as input
하지만 이제는 단일 이미지가
rather than just a single image.
아닌 여러 프레임을 입력으로 사용합니다.
So this is an example of many to one.
이것은 많은 입력에 대해 하나의 출력을 생성하는 예입니다.
And then you also have many to many.
그리고 또한 많은 입력에 대해 많은 출력을 생성하는 경우도 있습니다.
So the number of inputs and outputs in the sequences
시퀀스의 입력과 출력 수가 일치할 필요는 없으므로, 가변 개수의
don't need to match, so you could have your input
프레임을 입력으로 사용하고, 이
as a variable number of frames, and your output in this case
경우 출력은 가변 길이의 캡션이 될 수
could be a caption of variable length,
있으며, 반드시
and they don't need to necessarily match,
일치할 필요는 없지만 일치할
but they could match.
수도 있습니다.
So for every single input you have one output.
모든 입력에 대해 하나의 출력이 있습니다.
And for discussing RNNs we'll mainly
RNN에 대해 논의할 때 우리는 주로
be focusing on this setting on the far right.
오른쪽 끝의 설정에 집중할 것입니다.
But there are basically a lot of small changes
하지만 문제를 다른 설정에 적용하기
you can make to change and reformulate the problem to apply
위해 변경하고 재구성할 수 있는 작은 변화가 많이
to the other settings, but this is the most straightforward one.
있지만, 이것이 가장 직관적인 것입니다.
Every time there's an input, there's an output,
입력이 있을 때마다 출력이
and we'll be using it for the beginning of class
있으며, 수업 시작 부분에서 RNN이
to talk about how RNNs work.
어떻게 작동하는지 이야기하는 데 사용할 것입니다.
And a canonical example problem here
여기서 전형적인 예제
would be video classification, where you're
문제는 비디오 분류로,
classifying every single frame.
모든 프레임을 분류하는 것입니다.
OK, so what is an RNN?
좋습니다, RNN이란 무엇인가요?
The basic idea is you have an input sequence x, and an output
기본 아이디어는 입력 시퀀스 x와 출력 시퀀스 y가
sequence y.
있다는 것입니다.
And what makes an RNN an RNN is this recurrent nature.
RNN을 RNN으로 만드는 것은 이 순환적 특성입니다.
So often people will diagram it by this arrow that's
사람들은 종종 이 블록으로 피드백되는
feeding back into the block.
화살표로 이를 도식화합니다.
This is how you know it's a recurrent layer when you're
다양한 다이어그램을 읽을 때 이것이 순환
reading different diagrams.
레이어임을 알 수 있는 방법입니다.
But what it actually means is that RNNs
하지만 실제로 의미하는 것은 RNN이
have this internal state or a hidden state,
시퀀스가 처리될 때 업데이트되는 내부 상태
as it's often called, that is updated
또는 종종 '숨겨진 상태'를
as a sequence is processed.
가지고 있다는 것입니다.
So every time there's a new input to the model,
모델에 새로운 입력이 있을 때마다 이를
we process that and we calculate a new hidden state
처리하고 새로운 숨겨진 상태 또는 내부
or internal state.
상태를 계산합니다.
So there's a hidden state, it updates,
숨겨진 상태가 업데이트되며,
and it depends on the new inputs as well as the previous internal
이는 새로운 입력과 이전 내부
or hidden state.
또는 숨겨진 상태에 따라 달라집니다.
I think this diagram is sometimes a bit confusing
이 다이어그램은 기울기가 실제로
when you're trying to think about how the gradients are
어떻게 계산되는지와 연산 순서에 대해 생각할
actually calculated and what are the order of operations.
때 때때로 혼란스러울 수 있다고 생각합니다.
So people will often do this diagram of an unrolled RNN.
사람들은 종종 펼쳐진 RNN의 다이어그램을 그립니다.
And so here it's basically the same as before,
여기서 기본적으로 이전과 동일하지만,
but we're explicitly showing that the current hidden state
현재 숨겨진 상태 계산이 해당 시간
calculation is dependent on our input at that time step
단계의 입력과 이전 RNN 상태에
as well as the previous RNN state.
의존한다는 것을 명시적으로 보여줍니다.
So we're more explicitly modeling what is exactly
각 출력을 계산하는 데 정확히
needed to calculate each output, and each
필요한 것을 더 명시적으로 모델링하고
RNN you move backwards in the computational graph.
있으며, 각 RNN은 계산 그래프에서 뒤로 이동합니다.
So I've been speaking with words so far.
지금까지 단어로 이야기해왔습니다.
So let's formulate this with mathematical equations now.
이제 수학적 방정식으로 이를 정리해 보겠습니다.
So the basic idea is we're trying to process
기본 아이디어는 벡터 시퀀스 x를 처리하려고
a sequence of vectors, x.
한다는 것입니다.
And we're applying this recurrence formula
우리는 이 재귀 공식을 매 시간
at every single time step.
단계마다 적용하고 있습니다.
So we have our new hidden state as a function
따라서 우리는 이전 숨겨진 상태와 특정 시간
of the old hidden state and the input vector at some time step
단계의 입력 벡터의 함수로서 새로운 숨겨진 상태를
as well as we have a function with normally with an activation
가지고 있으며, 일반적으로 활성화 함수와
function along with some parameters,
일부 매개변수 W가
W. So you can think of this as this
있는 함수도 있습니다. 이것은 우리가 배우고
very similar to the initial neural network
있는 초기 신경망 레이어와 매우 유사하게
layers we were learning where it's a weight matrix,
생각할 수 있으며, 가중치
multiply by and then you follow it up by an activation function.
행렬을 곱한 다음 활성화 함수로 이어집니다.
This is the same thing here.
여기서도 같은 원리입니다.
The only change is that it's now a recurrence formula.
유일한 변화는 이제 재귀 공식이라는 것입니다.
So we're using the same set of W's and the same activation
우리는 숨겨진 상태를 계산할 때마다 같은 W 집합과 같은
function each time we're computing the hidden state.
활성화 함수를 사용하고 있습니다.
So basically, as I mentioned, this is a recurrence formula.
기본적으로 제가 언급한 바와 같이, 이것은 재귀 공식입니다.
And to get the actual output, so how do we
실제 출력을 얻기 위해, 이 파란색
calculate this blue block?
블록을 어떻게 계산합니까?
We have a separate function that depends
우리는 숨겨진 차원 상태를 출력
on a separate set of parameters that
차원으로 변환하는 별도의
convert our hidden dimension state into the dimension
매개변수 집합에 의존하는 별도의 함수를 가지고
of our output.
있습니다.
And also is a set of weights to convert the hidden state
또한 숨겨진 상태를 출력으로 변환하는 가중치
to the output.
집합도 있습니다.
So this does two and one.
따라서 이것은 두 가지 일을 합니다.
It changes the dimension of our vectors
우리의 벡터 차원을
from the dimension size of our hidden state, which
숨겨진 상태의 차원 크기에서
can be whatever we want to the dimension size of our output.
출력의 차원 크기로 변경합니다.
And then also it provides a transformation there.
그리고 또한 그곳에서 변환을 제공합니다.
So W hy is a weight matrix that you will multiply by your hidden
W hy는 숨겨진 상태에 곱하여 결과를 얻는 가중치 행렬입니다.
state to get the--
즉, 두 가지
so it does two things.
일을 합니다.
It converts your hidden state to the dimension of your output.
숨겨진 상태를 출력의 차원으로 변환합니다.
So your hidden state and output could be different dimensions.
따라서 숨겨진 상태와 출력은 서로 다른 차원을 가질 수 있습니다.
And then also, it's a weight matrix that you learn.
그리고 또한 배우는 가중치 행렬입니다.
So not only does it do this dimension change,
따라서 이 차원 변경을 수행할
but also it applies a transformation
뿐만 아니라 숨겨진 상태에
to your hidden state.
변환을 적용합니다.
So it's how you convert your hidden states
그래서 W hy는
to your outputs, what W hy is.
숨겨진 상태를 출력으로 변환하는 방법입니다.
So the previous slide was how we calculate the new hidden state.
이전 슬라이드는 새로운 숨겨진 상태를 계산하는 방법이었습니다.
So it's essentially the same idea
본질적으로 동일한 아이디어로, 같은
where you're doing this recursively with the same set
매개변수 집합으로 재귀적으로 수행하고 있지만,
of parameters, but we have one set
숨겨진 상태를 계산하기
of parameters and one function for calculating
위한 매개변수 집합과 함수가
the hidden state.
하나 있습니다.
We have another set of parameters and another function
출력을 계산하기 위한 매개변수
for calculating the output depending on what type of task
집합과 함수가 또 하나 있으며,
it is, and how we want to model the RNN.
이는 작업 유형과 RNN 모델링 방식에 따라 다릅니다.
Yeah, so they still share the same weights for each time step,
네, 그래서 여전히 각 시간 단계마다 같은 가중치를 공유하지만,
but there's two different things here.
여기에는 두 가지 다른 것이 있습니다.
One is to calculate basically how do you-- maybe
하나는 기본적으로 어떻게 계산하는지입니다.
it'll be more clear as we go through more concrete examples.
아마도 더 구체적인 예를 통해 더 명확해질 것입니다.
But how do you actually calculate the new hidden state,
하지만 새로운 숨겨진 상태를 실제로 어떻게 계산하는지,
which is this internal state of the RNN.
즉 RNN의 내부 상태입니다.
And then how do you convert that hidden state
그리고 그 숨겨진 상태를
to the output, which is this slide.
출력으로 변환하는 방법입니다. 이것이 이 슬라이드입니다.
So looking through this unrolled diagram here,
이 펼쳐진 다이어그램을 살펴보면, 숨겨진 상태를
we can see that you need to initialize your hidden state
어떤 값으로 초기화해야 하는지 알 수
to some value.
있습니다.
So we usually call this h,0 and you can initialize it
우리는 보통 이것을 h,0이라고 부르며 원하는 값으로 초기화할
to whatever you want.
수 있습니다.
In principle, usually this is a learned input vector,
원칙적으로, 보통 이것은 학습된 입력 벡터이지만, 이제
but now we'll specifically go into each step
우리는 이 펼쳐진 재귀 RNN의 각
of this unrolled recurrent RNN and actually
단계로 구체적인 예를 통해 실제로
go through a concrete example for what it looks like when
전방 패스를 수행하는 것이
you're doing the forward pass.
어떤 모습인지 살펴보겠습니다.
So one thing to note that already came up
이미 몇 가지 질문에서 언급된 바와
with some of the questions is that we're
같이, 우리는 벡터 x의
processing the sequence of vectors x,
시퀀스를 처리하고 있으며, 각 시간
and we're applying this recurrence formula at each time
단계에서 이 재귀 공식을 적용하고
step.
있습니다.
So you really do notice how the same function and the same set
숨겨진 상태를 계산할 때마다 같은 함수와 같은 매개변수
of parameters are used at every time step
집합이 사용되는 것을
when computing the hidden state.
정말로 알 수 있습니다.
And a separate function and a separate set of parameters
그리고 숨겨진 상태에서 출력을
are always used at each time step
예측할 때마다 항상
when predicting the output from the hidden state.
별도의 함수와 별도의 매개변수 집합이 사용됩니다.
Yeah, so can old values of y affect the new hidden state?
네, 그래서 이전 y 값이 새로운 은닉 상태에 영향을 줄 수 있나요?
Under some formulations, yes.
어떤 공식화에서는 그렇습니다.
And we'll actually go through one example of why that's used.
그리고 왜 그렇게 사용되는지에 대한 예제를 하나 살펴보겠습니다.
It's most commonly used if you want to predict the next--
가장 일반적으로 사용되는 경우는 다음 값을 예측하고자 할 때입니다.
if you're doing a language modeling or autoregressive
언어 모델링이나 자기 회귀 모델링
modeling task where you're trying
작업을 수행할 때 이전
to predict one value given the previous values,
값을 기반으로 하나의 값을 예측하려고
people will just use the previous values as the input.
할 때, 사람들은 이전 값을 입력으로 사용합니다.
So that's generally how people do
그래서 일반적으로 사람들이
that explicit formulation of how can y
y가 다음 은닉 상태에 어떻게 영향을 미칠 수
affect the next hidden state.
있는지에 대한 명시적 공식을 이렇게 사용합니다.
What is the difference between h and x at the first time step?
첫 번째 시간 단계에서 h와 x의 차이는 무엇인가요?
So they use basically different weights.
기본적으로 서로 다른 가중치를 사용합니다.
So the h,0 is using all of-- it's using the weights that are
h,0은 모든 은닉 상태를 다음 상태로 업데이트하는
used to update every hidden state to the next one.
데 사용되는 가중치를 사용하고 있습니다.
We'll go through exactly what the weights look like,
가중치가 어떻게 생겼는지 정확히 살펴보겠지만,
but basically they're using different weights,
기본적으로 서로 다른 가중치를
is the short answer.
사용하고 있다는 것이 짧은 대답입니다.
So when people say Vanilla RNN, they usually
사람들이 바닐라 RNN이라고
are almost exactly referring to this type of model
말할 때, 일반적으로 tanh 또는
where we have our hidden state t, which
쌍곡선 탄젠트를 활성화 함수로 사용하는
uses tanh or hyperbolic tangent as an activation function.
이 유형의 모델을 거의 정확하게 지칭합니다.
This is nice because it's bounded between 1
이것은 1과 -1 사이로 제한되기
and negative 1.
때문에 좋습니다.
So as you do the operation over and over again,
그래서 이 작업을 반복할수록 값이
your values will stay within this range.
이 범위 내에 유지됩니다.
So this is a nice property to have.
그래서 이것은 좋은 속성입니다.
It's also zero centered and you can
또한 0을 중심으로 하고
represent both positive and negative values.
양수와 음수를 모두 표현할 수 있습니다.
This is why people use tanh.
이것이 사람들이 tanh를 사용하는 이유입니다.
Also we sometimes have an output function fy here,
또한 여기서 출력 함수 fy가 있을 수 있지만, 가장 간단한
but in the simplest case your output yt
경우에는 출력 yt가 은닉
could just be a matrix multiplied by your hidden state.
상태와 곱해진 행렬일 수 있습니다.
So this is really the most simple formulation of an RNN.
그래서 이것이 RNN의 가장 간단한 공식입니다.
And what we'll specifically go in our concrete example
오늘 강의에서 구체적인 예제로
today in lecture is this idea of just manually creating
다룰 것은 수동으로 순환 신경망을 만드는
a recurrent neural network.
아이디어입니다.
So we're not going to learn this through gradient descent or all
그래디언트 하강법이나 다른 방법을 통해 배우지
these different methods.
않을 것입니다.
I'm just going to show you how you could construct one by hand.
어떻게 수작업으로 하나를 구성할 수 있는지 보여드리겠습니다.
And we'll go through it and you'll
그리고 그것을 살펴보면서
understand the forward pass, what
순전파가 어떻게 이루어지는지,
each of the different weight matrices are doing,
각 가중치 행렬이 무엇을 하는지,
as well as how the output is calculated.
출력이 어떻게 계산되는지 이해할 수 있을 것입니다.
So in this really toy example because it
이 간단한 예제에서는 모든
needs to be pretty simple, if we're just
가중치를 살펴보아야
going to be going through all the different weights.
하므로 꽤 단순해야 합니다.
You're given sequences of 0's and 1's, and your goal
0과 1의 시퀀스가 주어지고, 목표는 두
is to output a 1 when there's two repeated 1's in a row.
개의 연속된 1이 있을 때 1을 출력하는 것입니다.
So you're basically detecting repeated 1's and you'll
기본적으로 반복된 1을 감지하고, 그렇지
output a 0 otherwise.
않으면 0을 출력합니다.
So you can see this input sequence coming in 0, 1, 0, 1.
입력 시퀀스가 0, 1, 0, 1로 들어오는 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
So far, there's been no repeated ones.
지금까지 반복된 1은 없었습니다.
But now we have a repeated one, and we
하지만 이제 반복된 1이 있고,
have another repeated one because there's two in a row
여기서 두 개가 연속으로 있기 때문에 또
here and so on.
다른 반복된 1이 있습니다.
So this is the type of model we're building.
그래서 우리가 만들고 있는 모델의 유형입니다.
It's trying to do this task.
이 작업을 수행하려고 합니다.
This is specifically the many to many sequence modeling tasks
이것은 입력마다 하나의 출력을
where we have one output for every input.
갖는 다대다 시퀀스 모델링 작업입니다.
And so we've been talking high level so far,
지금까지 높은 수준에서 이야기했지만,
but if you're trying to create an RNN to do this,
이를 수행하기 위해 RNN을 만들려고
what information should be captured in the hidden state?
한다면, 은닉 상태에서 어떤 정보를 캡처해야 할까요?
So you have this internal state of your model, what
모델의 내부 상태가 있으므로,
information needs to be captured there in order to do this task?
이 작업을 수행하기 위해 어떤 정보가 그곳에 캡처되어야 할까요?
Yeah, so the input to the previous time step.
네, 그래서 이전 시간 단계의 입력입니다.
And if our output is only dependent on the hidden state,
그리고 우리의 출력이 숨겨진 상태에만 의존한다면, 우리는
what else do we need to know?
무엇을 더 알아야 할까요?
And the current--
현재-- 네,
Yeah, exactly.
정확히 그렇습니다.
So this is the information that we need
그래서 이것이 우리가 숨겨진
to capture in our hidden state.
상태에서 포착해야 할 정보입니다.
So previous input and the current value for x, so 0 or 1.
이전 입력과 현재 x 값, 즉 0 또는 1입니다.
And the way I'll do this is I'll just
이것을 하는 방법은 숨겨진 상태
set the hidden state t to be a three dimensional vector.
t를 3차원 벡터로 설정하는 것입니다.
The reason why it's 3, is this one will come in handy when
3인 이유는 출력 단계 계산을
we're trying to do the output stage calculation,
할 때 유용할 것이기 때문이지만,
but you could probably construct one without a 1 here.
여기서 1 없이도 만들 수 있을 것입니다.
This is just to make the math easy and simple
오늘 강의의 목적을 위해 수학을
for the purposes of the lecture today.
쉽게 하고 간단하게 만들기 위한 것입니다.
And the other information is the current value.
그리고 다른 정보는 현재 값입니다.
So this will either be 0 or 1 along with the previous values
그래서 이것은 이전 값 0 또는 1과 함께 0 또는
0 or 1.
1이 될 것입니다.
And we'll initialize it to be 001,
우리는 001로 초기화할 것이므로,
so that we're basically assuming it's basically seeing two zeros
기본적으로 이 시점에서 두 개의 0을
in a row before at this point.
연속으로 보고 있다고 가정하는 것입니다.
Yeah, so this is how we will do.
네, 그래서 이렇게 할 것입니다.
This will be the type of variables
이것이 우리가 숨겨진 상태에서
we're trying to track in our hidden state.
추적하려는 변수의 유형입니다.
And this is how we'll initialize h,0.
그리고 이것이 h,0을 초기화하는 방법입니다.
So I talked about how you can initialize it
다양한 전략으로 초기화할
to very different strategies, or you could learn it.
수 있거나 학습할 수 있다고 이야기했습니다.
This is what we'll initialize it to
이것이 우리가 초기화할
OK, now let's walk through the code
값입니다. 이제 코드를 단계별로
and I'll do it step by step.
살펴보겠습니다.
So I'm just putting it on screen here right now.
지금 화면에 표시하고 있습니다.
But we'll also do ReLU, I guess, sorry, one other thing
하지만 ReLU도 사용할 것이고, 미안합니다, 이 슬라이드에서 놓친 다른 한
I missed on this slide is that we're
가지는 활성화 함수를 ReLU로
setting our activation functions to be ReLU,
설정하고 있다는 것입니다. 수학을
just to make the math easy.
쉽게 하기 위해서입니다.
So it'll just be max of 0 or whatever the value is.
그래서 0 또는 그 값의 최대값이 될 것입니다.
We're only dealing essentially with zeros and ones
이 경우 기본적으로 0과 1만 다루고
in this case.
있습니다.
So it makes it pretty simple to think about.
그래서 생각하기가 꽤 간단합니다.
Yeah,
네, 아마도
You probably could construct it so that it works with tanh.
tanh와 함께 작동하도록 구성할 수 있을 것입니다.
But this is just something that I
하지만 이것은 실행
created as an example for how to run it.
방법에 대한 예제로 제가 만든 것입니다.
And so just to make the math really easy, we'll just do ReLU.
그래서 수학을 정말 쉽게 만들기 위해 ReLU를 사용할 것입니다.
But yeah, you could conceivably make a model
하지만 네, tanh로도 할 수
that could do this with tanh.
있는 모델을 만들 수 있을 것입니다.
Yeah, cool.
네, 멋지네요.
So we have ReLU.
우리는 ReLU를 가지고 있습니다.
We have two specific weights here.
여기 두 개의 특정 가중치가 있습니다.
We have the first weight, which converts
첫 번째 가중치는 이전
our previous hidden state.
숨겨진 상태를 변환합니다.
It applies a transformation to the previous hidden state
이전 숨겨진 상태에 변환을
onto to calculate the next one.
적용하여 다음 것을 계산합니다.
And then we have this weight here,
그리고 이 가중치는
which converts our input x to the dimension of our hidden
입력 x를 숨겨진 상태의 차원으로
state, as well as applies a transformation.
변환하고 변환을 적용합니다.
So we are setting this second one.
그래서 우리는 이 두 번째 것을 설정하고 있습니다.
So our current hidden state is a function
현재의 은닉 상태는
of the previous hidden state, along with the current time
이전 은닉 상태와 현재 시간 단계의
step.
함수입니다.
And so when we're trying to calculate this hidden state
따라서 시간 단계 t에서 이 은닉
at time step t, we're looking to calculate this current value
상태를 계산할 때, 먼저 현재 값을 계산하려고
first.
합니다.
So we'll use the x value here.
여기서 x 값을 사용할 것입니다.
We'll set the weight to be a 3 by 1 column vector with values
가중치를 1, 0, 0의 값을 가진 3x1 열 벡터로
1, 0, 0, such that when x is 0 and we do the matrix multiply,
설정하여 x가 0일 때 행렬 곱을 하면 0 벡터가
we get a 0 vector, and when x is 1, we'll get 1, 0, 0.
되고, x가 1일 때는 1, 0, 0이 되도록 합니다.
And we'll add this to another term,
그리고 이것을 다른 항에
but basically, this is going to be calculating
추가할 것이지만, 기본적으로 현재
what is the current value here.
값을 계산하는 것입니다.
So it'll be either a zero on top or a one on top.
그래서 위에는 0이거나 1이 될 것입니다.
And it's calculated based on this first operation here.
이것은 여기서 첫 번째 연산을 기반으로 계산됩니다.
So that's how we're calculating the current value
그래서 입력을 기반으로
based on the input.
현재 값을 계산하는 방법입니다.
Now we'll talk about, how are we doing this hidden state
이제 은닉 상태 변환을 어떻게 하는지에 대해
transformation.
이야기하겠습니다.
So we want to just use the current value for this top value
위의 이 값에 대해 현재 값을 사용하고자
here.
합니다.
So in our weight matrix, we'll just have zeros in the top row.
가중치 행렬의 상단 행에는 0만 있을 것입니다.
This means that when we multiply it
이는 이전 은닉 상태와
with the previous hidden state we'll
곱할 때 위쪽에 0
get a 0 value here for the top.
값을 얻게 됨을 의미합니다.
So it'll be 0 plus whatever value the right hand
그래서 오른쪽에 있는 값에 따라 0과
side contains.
더해질 것입니다.
So that's how we're going to maintain this not changing based
이렇게 해서 이전 은닉 상태에 따라 변경되지
on the previous hidden state.
않도록 유지할 것입니다.
And we'll set it to be 1, 0, 0 for the next row.
다음 행은 1, 0, 0으로 설정할 것입니다.
Why we do this?
왜 이렇게 하는 걸까요?
Is you can imagine we have the hidden
우리가 여기에서 이전 시간 단계의 숨겨진
state from the previous time step here.
상태를 가지고 있다고 상상할 수 있습니다.
And we want to set the now previous
그리고 우리는 이제 이전 값을 이전 현재 시간 단계로
to be the former current time step.
설정하고자 합니다.
So we have a 1, 0, 0.
그래서 우리는 1, 0, 0을 가지고 있습니다.
What this will do is it'll multiply by h,t minus 1.
이것은 h,t-1과 곱해질 것입니다.
We'll set the current value over to now the previous value
현재 값을 이제 이 시간 단계의 이전
for this time step.
값으로 설정할 것입니다.
So basically this term will be a zero on top,
기본적으로 이 항은 위에 0이
and it will be whatever the previous time step input
되고, 두 번째 항은 이전 시간 단계
value was as the second term.
입력 값이 됩니다.
And then this final bit here just maintains the one
그리고 마지막 부분은 모든
so that we're keeping this one across all calculations.
계산에서 이 1을 유지하도록 합니다.
So just to recap, we have zeros here
요약하자면, 우리는
because we want the right hand side term to be
오른쪽 항이 현재 값을
tracking this current value.
추적하도록 0이 있습니다.
We have a one here to copy over the current from the former time
여기에는 이전 시간 단계의
step to be the previous--
현재 값을
sorry to copy the current of the former time step
현재 시간 단계의 이전으로
to be the previous of the current time step.
복사하기 위해 1이 있습니다.
So we're just doing h--
우리는 h를 하고 있습니다.
maybe it's easy in the code but h,t previous is equal to h,t,
코드에서는 쉬울 수 있지만 h,t 이전은 h,t와 같고,
and we want to also move the corresponding value down one
여기에 해당 값을 아래로 하나
here.
이동하고자 합니다.
And then this is just a copy of the one.
그리고 이것은 1의 복사본입니다.
So how do we actually get our output now?
그렇다면 실제로 출력을 어떻게 얻을 수 있을까요?
So we basically talked about how we can track these values given
우리는 Whh와 Wxh에 대해 이야기한 가중치 행렬을
the weight matrices I talked about, so Whh and Wxh
통해 이러한 값을 추적할 수 있는 방법에 대해 이야기했습니다.
So if we have a weight matrix to convert
숨겨진 상태를 출력 차원으로
our hidden state into the output dimension,
변환하는 가중치 행렬이 필요하며,
we want it to be 1 by 3.
우리는 1x3이 되기를 원합니다.
So it's a single value that's being output when we have
숨겨진 차원을 입력으로 할 때 출력되는
this hidden dimension as input.
단일 값입니다.
And this is a dot product between the values here
그리고 이것은 여기의 값과 여기의 값 간의
and the values here.
내적입니다.
So what this will correspond to is the current
이것은 현재 값과 이전 값에서 1을 빼는
plus the previous minus 1 because we multiply the minus 1
것과 관련이 있습니다. 왜냐하면 여기에서 -1과 곱하기
here.
때문입니다.
This is where the one became useful,
여기서 하나가 유용해지고
and the current associated here with a one.
현재는 하나와 연결됩니다.
And then also the previous associated here with the one
그리고 이전도 여기서
as well.
하나와 연결됩니다.
So that's how we actually do it.
그래서 우리가 실제로 이렇게 합니다.
And if you think about it, this general formula will work.
생각해보면 이 일반적인 공식이 작동할 것입니다.
So if say we're looking here, we have the current plus
여기서 현재와 이전을 더하면 2에서 1을
the previous is 2 minus 1 is 1 for this left hand
빼면 ReLU 내부의 이 왼쪽 항은
term inside the ReLU.
1이 됩니다.
So the max of 1 and 0 is 1.
1과 0의 최대값은 1입니다.
And if these are both 0, you'll have a minus 1, so we'll get 0.
둘 다 0이라면 -1이 되어 0이 됩니다.
These are a 1 and a 0.
이들은 1과 0입니다.
Then you'll still get 0.
그럼에도 불구하고 0이 나옵니다.
So these are how you can construct these weight matrices.
이렇게 가중치 행렬을 구성할 수 있습니다.
But I actually wanted to pause briefly and talk about
하지만 이 계산의 각 단계에 대해 질문이 있는지 잠시
if there were any questions about any step
멈추고 이야기하고 싶었습니다. 왜냐하면
among this calculation, because this is the only example we'll
이 수업에서 우리가 실제로 모든 행렬과 벡터 곱셈을
go through in class, where we're literally doing all the matrix
수행하는 유일한 예제이기 때문입니다.
and vector multiplications, and the rest
나머지는 사람들이
will be more high level explanations for how people tend
이러한 레이어를 어떻게 조합하는지에 대한 더 높은
to put these layers together.
수준의 설명이 될 것입니다.
So I just want to pause and see if there's a question about how
그래서 행렬과 벡터가 어떻게 추적되고 곱해지고
the matrices and vectors are tracked and multiplied
업데이트되는지에 대한 질문이 있는지
and updated.
확인하고 싶습니다.
Yeah, so the question is, how do you
네, 질문은 가중치
go about constructing the weight matrices?
행렬을 어떻게 구성하느냐입니다.
Which is a really great question,
정말 좋은 질문이고, 여기
and I thought to put it in the slide here.
슬라이드에 넣으려고 생각했습니다.
So how would you actually do this?
그럼 실제로 어떻게 할까요?
It's the same way we're always finding the weight
이 수업에서 항상 가중치 행렬을 찾는
matrices in this class.
방법과 같습니다.
We're going to be using gradient descent.
우리는 경량 하강법을 사용할 것입니다.
And we'll talk about how you do gradient descent when
여러 시간 단계가 있을 때 경량 하강법을 어떻게
you have multiple time steps, and maybe you
수행하는지, 각 시간 단계에서 손실이
have losses computed at each time step as well.
계산될 수 있는 방법에 대해 이야기할 것입니다.
So that'll be a lot of what we go into right next.
그래서 그게 우리가 다음에 다룰 많은 내용이 될 것입니다.
So it's a great question and very relevant to the lecture.
그래서 좋은 질문이고 강의와 매우 관련이 있습니다.
So this is just an example, so you
이것은 단지 예제일 뿐이므로
can see how all of the weight matrices are multiplied.
모든 가중치 행렬이 어떻게 곱해지는지 볼 수 있습니다.
Basically, if you were trying to change--
기본적으로 만약 당신이
if you were trying to initialize with this,
이것으로 초기화하려고 하고,
and then train it to do another task,
그런 다음 다른 작업을 수행하도록
that would be transfer learning where you're initializing
훈련하려고 한다면, 그것은 이로 가중치를 초기화하는
the weights with this.
전이 학습이 될 것입니다.
But in practice, I don't think it would work very well at all,
하지만 실제로는 잘 작동하지 않을 것이라고 생각합니다. 왜냐하면 당신의
because your hidden state is really small
숨겨진 상태가 정말 작고 사람들은
and people normally do much larger hidden states.
일반적으로 훨씬 더 큰 숨겨진 상태를 사용하기 때문입니다.
I just wanted to do something that I could fit in the slide
여기 슬라이드에 맞출 수 있는 무언가를
here.
하고 싶었습니다.
Yeah, OK, I'll go over the second row again.
네, 알겠습니다. 두 번째 행을 다시 설명하겠습니다.
So if you imagine we have h,t minus 1 as a column vector here,
h,t-1을 열 벡터로 상상해보면, 행렬 곱셈을
when you do the matrix multiply, to get the value of the left
수행하여 여기 왼쪽의 값을 얻을 때,
hand side here, what this second row is doing is you're taking
이 두 번째 행은 값을 가져와서
the value, and then you're rotating it and doing the dot
회전시키고 여기 있는 값들과
product with the values here.
내적을 수행합니다.
So for the second row that gets calculated,
계산된 두 번째 행의 항목은
the entry here will be equal to the top of the vector here.
여기 벡터의 맨 위와 같습니다.
So this is how we move the current down to the previous
그래서 현재를 이전으로 이동하는 방법은 여기
is in this step here.
단계에서 이루어집니다.
So the end result of this matrix multiply
이 행렬 곱셈의
will be such that the second value is the current value
최종 결과는 두 번째 값이 t-1의 현재
from t minus 1.
값이 되도록 합니다.
So we do the matrix multiply with t minus 1 here,
그래서 t-1과 행렬 곱셈을 수행하고,
and so the second row of this operation and this operation
이 연산의 두 번째 행과 이 연산은 모두
are both giving us vectors of the size of our hidden state.
우리의 숨겨진 상태 크기의 벡터를 제공합니다.
And so we're adding them together.
그래서 우리는 그것들을 더하고 있습니다.
Yeah, the left is doing the previous carryover
네, 왼쪽은 이전 이월을 수행하고
and the right is doing the current.
오른쪽은 현재를 수행하고 있습니다.
And that's also of how it works for RNNs when you are doing it
그리고 이것이 장난감 예제를 넘어 RNN에서 어떻게
beyond this toy example, where this weight matrix is being
작동하는지를 보여줍니다. 여기서 이 가중치 행렬은
multiplied by the current input, and this other weight matrix
현재 입력과 곱해지고, 이 다른
is being multiplied by the previous hidden state.
가중치 행렬은 이전 은닉 상태와 곱해집니다.
So that's what these weight matrices track more generally
그래서 이것이 이러한 가중치 행렬이 특정
than the specific problem as well.
문제보다 더 일반적으로 추적하는 것입니다.
So how do you actually compute the gradients?
그렇다면 실제로 기울기를 어떻게 계산합니까?
Let's look at the computational graph.
계산 그래프를 살펴보겠습니다.
So just to draw a little bit more explicitly than before,
그래서 이전보다 좀 더 명확하게 그리기 위해,
we have these x1 coming in and x2,
우리는 x1과 x2가 들어오고, x의
and we have a sequence of x's.
시퀀스가 있습니다.
We're calculating a hidden state at each time step,
우리는 각 시간 단계에서 은닉 상태를
and we're specifically using the same W's, same weight
계산하고 있으며, 이러한 계산을 위해 동일한
matrices for each of these calculations as well.
W, 동일한 가중치 행렬을 사용하고 있습니다.
So we need to be thinking about this
그래서 우리는 기울기를
when we're thinking about how we're computing the gradients,
계산하는 방법을 생각할 때 이것을 고려해야 하며, 많은 입력에서
and let's start with the many to many scenario.
많은 출력 시나리오로 시작하겠습니다.
So we have an output for each input.
각 입력에 대한 출력이 있습니다.
And in this scenario, you can often also calculate
이 시나리오에서는 각 출력에 대한 손실을 계산할 수도 있으며,
a loss for each output, which is how correct
이는 해당 단계에서 출력이
is the output at that stage.
얼마나 정확한지를 나타냅니다.
So if we're doing this setting you have a loss at each step,
따라서 이 설정에서 각 단계에서 손실이 있으며, 이를 모두 합쳐
and you can sum them all together to get your total loss.
총 손실을 얻을 수 있습니다.
And this would be your loss across the entire input
이것이 전체 입력 시퀀스에
sequence.
대한 손실입니다.
And when we do backprop basically,
그리고 기본적으로 역전파를 수행할 때, 최종 손실을 계산하면
when we compute our final loss, we
각 시간
can then calculate the loss per time step
단계에 대한 손실도
as well or depending on the formulation.
계산할 수 있습니다.
So if we're calculating a loss per time step,
따라서 시간 단계별로 손실을 계산하는 경우, 이를
you can treat them independently.
독립적으로 처리할 수 있습니다.
Sometimes you have an overall loss based
때때로 시간 단계별 손실을
on the loss per time step too.
기반으로 전체 손실이 있을 수도 있습니다.
We can also get basically the final gradients for each
우리는 이러한 W 각각에 대한 최종 기울기를 얻을
of these W's.
수 있습니다.
You can calculate the gradient for each time step separately,
각 시간 단계에 대해 기울기를 별도로 계산한
and then you're going to sum them all together.
다음, 이를 모두 합칠 것입니다.
So this is how it works in practice.
이것이 실제로 작동하는 방식입니다.
You could imagine if it were different W's at each time step.
각 시간 단계에서 다른 W가 있었다고 상상할 수 있습니다.
You could pretty probably easily see how the computational graph
각기 다른 W에 대해 다른 기울기를 계산할 수 있도록
could be structured such that you're calculating a different
계산 그래프가 구조화될 수
gradient for each of these different W's.
있는 방법을 쉽게 볼 수 있습니다.
And so we're essentially treating our single W
그래서 우리는 본질적으로 계산 목적으로
for computational purposes as a set of different W's, but then
단일 W를 서로 다른 W 집합으로 취급하지만, 마지막에는 모든 기울기를
at the end, we merge all the gradients together
합칩니다. 왜냐하면 곱해지는
because it's just the same weight
것은 동일한 가중치
matrix that's being multiplied.
행렬이기 때문입니다.
So conceptually, you can think of it as you're just calculating
개념적으로, 각 시간 단계에 대해 계산하고 있는 것으로
it for each time step, almost treating it in your head
생각할 수 있으며, 머릿속에서 마치
like it's a different W being used,
다른 W를 사용하는 것처럼
but because it's the same value of the weights,
처리하지만, 가중치의 값이
you just need to sum all the gradients that you calculate
동일하기 때문에 각 시간 단계에서
at each time step together.
계산한 모든 기울기를 합쳐야 합니다.
In the many to one scenario, you'll
많은 입력에서 하나의
just have a single loss calculated here.
출력 시나리오에서는 여기에서 단일 손실만 계산됩니다.
And sometimes you'll only use the final hidden state
때때로 문제 설정에 따라 최종 은닉 상태만
to calculate the value depending on the problem setting.
사용하여 값을 계산합니다.
Say you're trying to do video classification,
예를 들어 비디오 분류를 시도하는
it may make sense to use the hidden state from every step,
경우, 분류하는 동안 비디오 전체에 대한 정보를
because you might have information about the video
가질 수 있으므로 각 단계의 은닉
throughout the entire course of the video during classification.
상태를 사용하는 것이 의미가 있을 수 있습니다.
You're going to do some pooling, like average pooling or max
당신은 평균 풀링이나 최대 풀링과
pooling or something like that to compute your y value.
같은 풀링을 수행하여 y 값을 계산할 것입니다.
And then if you have this one to many mapping like in image
그리고 이미지 분류나 이미지 캡셔닝에서 이전 y를 통합하는
classification or sorry, in image captioning,
방법에 대한 질문이 있었던 것처럼, 이러한 일대다
there was a question about how you could incorporate
매핑이 있을 경우에도
the previous y's.
마찬가지입니다.
So you still need to have an input to your f,w
따라서 f,w에 대한 입력이 필요합니다. 왜냐하면 두 개의 서로
because it's two different of these weight matrices,
다른 가중치 행렬이기 때문입니다.
one that's expecting input vector x,
하나는 입력 벡터 x를 기대하고,
and the other that's expecting the previous time steps hidden
다른 하나는 이전 시간 단계의 은닉 상태를 기대합니다.
state.
그래서 여기 많은 값을 넣을 수 있다고 상상할 수 있습니다.
You could just put zeros or you could put the previous output
당신은 단순히 0을 넣거나 이전 출력을 여기에
here.
넣을 수 있습니다.
So I explained at a high level how you do the back propagation.
나는 역전파를 수행하는 방법을 높은 수준에서 설명했습니다.
But there's actually some specific issues
하지만 실제로는 GPU
that you'll run into when you're trying this conceptual--
메모리가 부족해지는 것과 같은 특정
when you're looking through this conceptual framework that
문제에 직면하게 될 것입니다.
are very practical in terms of running out of GPU memory, which
이는 신경망을 훈련할 때 발생하는
is always the cause of basically all the issues when you're
모든 문제의 원인입니다. 그리고,
trying to train a neural network that and,
아마도 NaN 손실 문자열 훈련과
I guess, NaN loss string training.
관련이 있습니다.
So when you're computing, say, a loss at each time step,
따라서 각 시간 단계에서 손실을 계산할 때, 매우 긴
and you have an extremely long input sequence,
입력 시퀀스가 있는 경우 이해하기가
it's really easy to understand.
정말 쉽습니다.
You need to be keeping the activations and the gradients
각 시간 단계에서 활성화와 기울기를
at each time step in memory and then summing them all together.
메모리에 유지하고 모두 합산해야 합니다.
This is going to get extremely large as your input sequence
입력 시퀀스가 증가함에 따라 매우 커질
increases.
것입니다.
So what can you do practically to resolve this issue?
이 문제를 해결하기 위해 실제로 무엇을 할 수 있을까요?
This is called backpropagation through time,
이것은 시간에 따른 역전파라고
by the way, when you have the same weight matrix that's
하며, 여러 다른 시간 단계에서
being applied in multiple different time steps,
적용되는 동일한 가중치 행렬이
and then you're summing the gradient at each time step
있을 때, 각 시간 단계에서 기울기를
together.
합산하는 것입니다.
So what you can do is, it's called
할 수 있는 것은 잘라진 시간에
truncated back propagation through time.
따른 역전파라고 합니다.
So you basically fix a time window,
기본적으로 시간 창을
and you can look at basically pretending
고정하고, 지금까지 모델이
that this is all the model was trained on so far.
훈련된 것처럼 가정할 수 있습니다.
We start with our h,0.
h,0에서 시작합니다.
We calculate based on the input at time step 1,
시간 단계 1의 입력과 이전 h 값을
and our previous h value.
기반으로 계산합니다.
We can calculate what is the current hidden state at h,1,
현재 숨겨진 상태 h,1을 계산할 수 있으며, 이를 사용하여
and then we can use that to calculate our output.
출력을 계산할 수 있습니다.
We'll have our loss.
손실을 얻게 됩니다.
And we can run this for each of our examples.
각 예제에 대해 이 작업을 수행할 수 있습니다.
And you can imagine how in this setting,
이 설정에서 훈련 중에
it's relatively easy to see how you just treat the beginning
우리가 보는 모든 것이 시작 시퀀스처럼 처리하는
sequence as if this is all we're seeing during training.
것이 얼마나 쉬운지 상상할 수 있습니다.
And moving to the next block, now essentially,
다음 블록으로 이동하면 이제
you're starting your h,0 with now it's the output
h,0이 이전 단계의
of your previous step here.
출력으로 시작됩니다.
So we're initializing the hidden state with whatever the output
따라서 마지막 단계에서의 출력을 사용하여 숨겨진
was in our final step, but the gradients
상태를 초기화하지만, 기울기는
are no longer carrying over.
더 이상 전달되지 않습니다.
So we're basically batching the computational graph such
기본적으로 시간 단계의 이웃에서
that we're only looking at the loss in the neighborhood
손실만 보고 있는 계산 그래프를
of these time steps at a time.
배치하고 있습니다.
This is a fixed window size that you set.
이것은 설정하는 고정 창 크기입니다.
So this is how you get around this relatively, I would say,
이것이 특히 긴 입력 시퀀스가 있을 때 상대적으로
common issue, especially as you have really long input
일반적인 문제를 해결하는
sequences.
방법입니다.
And so yeah, you basically are batching it out,
그래서 기본적으로 배치 처리하고
and you can just keep doing this for the entire input sequence.
전체 입력 시퀀스에 대해 계속할 수 있습니다.
So one other thing is that you might ask,
또 다른 질문은, 마지막에 단일 출력을 가진
how does this work, if we have just a single output
경우 어떻게 작동하는지
at the very end?
물어볼 수 있습니다.
So you can still calculate the gradients at each time step,
각 시간 단계에서 기울기를 여전히
but you will no longer have this loss that's
계산할 수 있지만, 더 이상 시간 단계 자체의 출력에
dependent on the time step itself,
의존하는 손실은 없으며,
the output of the
대신 상류
rather you'll be relying on upstream gradients.
기울기에 의존하게 됩니다.
So you can imagine we're looking at the far right of the diagram
여기 다이어그램의 가장 오른쪽을 보고
here, and we have our loss that we
있으며, 마지막 시간 단계의
calculate based on the output of the final time step.
출력을 기반으로 계산한 손실이 있습니다.
We can calculate what is the gradient with respect
현재 숨겨진 상태에 대한
to our current hidden state at the end.
기울기를 계산할 수 있습니다.
And then we have our Whh matrix to help us understand
그리고 이전 숨겨진 상태가 최종 숨겨진 상태에
how did the previous hidden state contribute
어떻게 기여했는지 이해하는 데 도움이
to the final hidden state.
되는 Whh 행렬이 있습니다.
And we can use that to calculate the gradient
이것을 사용하여 이전 숨겨진 상태와 가중치 행렬을
and understanding based on the previous hidden state
기반으로 기울기를 계산할
and the weight matrix.
수 있습니다.
How can we change this transformation matrix Whh such
손실을 변경할 수 있도록 이 변환 행렬 Whh를
that we would be changing our loss?
어떻게 변경할 수 있을까요?
And then basically just applying the gradient rule to Whh
그리고 기본적으로 여기서 Whh에 대해 기울기 규칙을 반복적으로
over and over again here.
적용합니다.
And you're only looking at how the hidden state changed
숨겨진 상태가 다음 숨겨진 상태를 어떻게
the next hidden state, and how that contributed to the loss.
변화시켰는지, 그리고 그것이 손실에 어떻게 기여했는지를 보고 있습니다.
So you look at the final example here.
여기 마지막 예제를 봅니다.
This tells you how changing the hidden state
이것은 숨겨진 상태를 변경하는
depends on the loss, and then how the previous hidden states,
것이 손실에 어떻게 의존하는지를 알려주며, 이전
how they change, how that affected
숨겨진 상태가 어떻게 변화했는지,
the current hidden state which is given by this Whh matrix.
그것이 현재 숨겨진 상태에 어떻게 영향을 미쳤는지를 보여줍니다.
So using different W's at each time step
각 시간 단계에서 서로 다른 W를 사용하면 더
would essentially mean that you're no longer modeling it
이상 재귀 관계로 모델링하지 않는다는
as a recurrence relation.
것을 의미합니다.
So basically you can think of it as one layer
기본적으로 각 가능한 시간 단계에 대해 하나의
for each different possible time step.
레이어로 생각할 수 있습니다.
So you would probably see worse performance
따라서 재귀적으로 시퀀스로 모델링하지
because if you are no longer modeling it as a sequence
않으면 성능이 저하될 것입니다. 각 입력이
recursively, you're just--
독립적으로 가는 별도의
imagine you train a neural network
가중치를
where you have a series of inputs,
가진 신경망을
each one has a separate weight that it goes to--
훈련한다고 상상해
Independently.
보세요.
Yeah, independently.
네, 독립적으로요.
That would make sense for a problem
순서 모델링 문제가
where it's not a sequence modeling problem,
아닌 문제에 대해서는 이해가
you just have a set of things that you want to classify.
됩니다. 분류하고 싶은 것들의 집합이 있을 뿐입니다.
You will need to know the amount of the sequence ahead of time.
시퀀스의 양을 미리 알아야 합니다.
So I think it could work if it's not a sequence,
그래서 시퀀스가 아니라면
but for sequences of variable length,
작동할 수 있을 것 같지만, 가변 길이의 시퀀스에
I think it would not work very well because you're--
대해서는 잘 작동하지 않을 것 같습니다.
I mean I'm trying to think of a simple way to explain it,
왜냐하면 각 시간 단계마다 하나의
but it's like you're just training
신경망을 훈련시키는
one neural network for each time step,
것과 같기 때문입니다. 그래서
so it's not the way to formulate it.
그렇게 공식화하는 방법이 아닙니다.
So how does this work with chunking?
그럼 청킹과는 어떻게 작동하나요?
So we have our--
그래서 여기서 빨간 점이 있는
do you understand how to this point, at the point
지점까지 이해하셨나요?
right here where the red dot, we can calculate
우리는 최종 은닉 상태에 대한
the gradient of the loss with respect
손실의 기울기를 계산할
to our final hidden state?
수 있습니다.
So if we can do that, then we can calculate the gradient
그렇게 할 수 있다면, 우리는 두 번째 최종 은닉
of our loss with respect to our second to final hidden state.
상태에 대한 손실의 기울기를 계산할 수 있습니다.
Because we know our final hidden state
최종 은닉 상태는 이전
is dependent on our previous hidden state times this weight
은닉 상태에 이 가중치 행렬 W를 곱한
matrix W.
것에 의존하기 때문입니다.
So we can do this and we can go back and forth until here.
그래서 우리는 이렇게 할 수 있고 여기까지 왔다 갔다 할 수 있습니다.
And at this point, all we need to save is this final step here.
이 시점에서 우리가 저장해야 할 것은 이 마지막 단계입니다.
So what is the gradient of this very final or finals--
그럼 이 마지막 또는 최종 은닉 상태의 기울기는 무엇인가요? 아마도 '최종'이라는 단어를 사용하는 것이
maybe over using the word final.
적절하지 않을 수 있습니다.
But what is the gradient of this initial hidden state
하지만 잘라낸 배치 내에서 이 초기 은닉 상태의
within our truncated batch, with respect to the loss?
기울기는 손실에 대해 무엇인가요?
And then when we're calculating backwards,
그리고 역으로 계산할 때,
we just use that value to calculate all the previous time
우리는 그 값을 사용하여 모든 이전 시간 단계를
steps.
계산합니다.
So that's the overall process.
그래서 그게 전체 과정입니다.
You're only looking at how the hidden state transforms
당신은 은닉 상태가 새로운 은닉 상태를 형성하는 방식만
to form the new hidden state, and that's the only value
보고 있으며, 여기서 업데이트되는
that's getting updated here.
유일한 값입니다.
Yeah, and also how the input changes the hidden state.
네, 그리고 입력이 은닉 상태를 어떻게 변화시키는지도요.
So you're looking at two values, both how the input affects it,
그래서 두 가지 값을 보고 있습니다. 입력이
and how the input affects the next hidden state
그것에 미치는 영향과 입력이 다음 은닉
and the previous hidden state.
상태와 이전 은닉 상태에 미치는 영향입니다.
Sorry, there's two values, yeah.
죄송합니다, 두 가지 값이 있습니다.
So the learning still occurs for all the batches.
그래서 학습은 모든 배치에 대해 여전히 발생합니다.
So you have your loss with respect
여기 W의 각
to each of your parameters in W here.
매개변수에 대한 손실이 있습니다.
And then when you're calculating it for the previous time step,
그리고 이전 시간 단계에 대해 계산할 때,
you basically keep this one value.
기본적으로 이 하나의 값을 유지합니다.
If you change the initial hidden state here,
여기 초기 은닉 상태를 변경하면 손실이
how does that change the loss?
어떻게 변하나요?
You can calculate that, and then you
그것을 계산할 수 있고,
can see how all the variables feeding into this, namely
그러면 이 원래 은닉 상태와 현재
this original hidden state and the current time
시간 단계가 이 변수에 어떻게
step, how will that affect the variable?
영향을 미칠지 볼 수 있습니다.
But then when you're actually moving to the next chunk over,
하지만 실제로 다음 청크로 이동할 때,
you only need to look at how does this hidden state here
이 은닉 상태가 다음 청크의 은닉 상태에
affect the hidden state on in the next chunk.
어떻게 영향을 미치는지만 살펴보면 됩니다.
So you're looking at this division boundary.
그래서 이 분할 경계를 보고 있습니다.
The one variable you need to track over
추적해야 할 유일한
is what is the gradient of the hidden state that
변수는 청크 이후에 발생하는 은닉 상태의
occurs after the chunk.
기울기가 무엇인지입니다.
And then you can use that to calculate
그런 다음 이를 사용하여
the gradient of the current hidden state, which
입력 x와 이전에 의존하는 현재
is dependent on the input x and the previous.
은닉 상태의 기울기를 계산할 수 있습니다.
So there's different ways you can formulate it,
공식화하는 방법은 여러 가지가
but you can imagine we just apply
있지만, 우리는 여기 모든 가중치에
the update to all the weights here and we zero out the memory.
업데이트를 적용하고 메모리를 제로화한다고 상상할 수 있습니다.
The only thing we're tracking is this gradient right here.
우리가 추적하는 유일한 것은 바로 이 기울기입니다.
So you can apply, you can do gradient apply step
그래서 기울기를 가중치에 적용하는
where you apply all the gradients to the weights
단계에서 학습률과 최적화 도구에
depend on the learning rate and your optimizer and all
따라 모든 기울기를 적용할 수
this stuff.
있습니다.
And then you move on to calculating the next batch.
그런 다음 다음 배치를 계산하는 것으로 넘어갑니다.
So the reason why this isn't a perfect calculation
이것이 완벽한 계산이 아닌 이유는
is because you're calculating these independently rather than
모든 것을 한 번에 계산하는 것이 아니라 독립적으로 계산하고
all at once.
있기 때문입니다.
So you have three different updates rather than
그래서 한 번에 하나의 업데이트가 아니라
just one update at a time, but it should be--
세 가지 다른 업데이트가 있습니다.
you still calculating the gradient for each step here.
하지만 여전히 각 단계에서 기울기를 계산해야 합니다.
You keep one thing in memory, which
메모리에 하나의 것을 유지하는데,
is how does this hidden state-- the first one in the batch.
그것은 이 숨겨진 상태가 배치에서 첫 번째 것이라는 것입니다.
How can you update the hidden state here
여기서 손실을 결정하기 위해 숨겨진
to determine the loss?
상태를 어떻게 업데이트할 수 있습니까?
And we throw out all the other ones.
그리고 나머지는 모두 버립니다.
So you have the weights in memory.
그래서 메모리에 가중치가 있습니다.
You can apply the gradient, you do your learning rate multiply
기울기를 적용할 수 있고, 학습률을 곱한
and you apply it to the weights.
후 가중치에 적용합니다.
You'll also see a similar thing if you do distributed learning.
분산 학습을 하면 비슷한 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
So if you have a gradient calculated on each GPU
각 GPU에서 독립적으로
separately, they will apply them all to the same set of weights
계산된 기울기를 모두 동일한 가중치
even though they're calculated independently.
집합에 적용합니다.
So I think we have a lecture on distributed learning coming up.
분산 학습에 대한 강의가 곧 있을 것 같습니다.
So it's a similar thing where you're not tracking it
모두 같은 메모리에서 동시에
all in the same memory at the same time,
추적하지 않고, 가중치에
and you're applying it to the weights one at a time.
하나씩 적용하는 비슷한 상황입니다.
Yeah, it would be better if you could fit it all in memory.
모두 메모리에 맞출 수 있다면 더 좋을 것입니다.
I mean, this is mainly--
이것은 주로--
for this one, it's essentially the same.
이 경우에는 본질적으로 동일합니다.
But in this setting maybe it's more clear
하지만 이 설정에서는 정보를 명시적으로
how you're explicitly losing information.
잃고 있다는 것이 더 명확할 수 있습니다.
So here, you're only looking at some of the outputs at a time.
여기서는 한 번에 일부 출력만 보고 있습니다.
So it's really clear how we're not
계산할 때 모든 손실 집합을 보지
looking at the entire set of the losses
않는 것이 정말 명확합니다. 각 시간
when we're calculating, because there's
단계에서 손실이
losses at each time step.
있기 때문입니다.
So you lose information here, but in this case,
여기서 정보를 잃지만, 이
you wouldn't lose information.
경우에는 정보를 잃지 않습니다.
I think one more practical example where
전체 RNN을 슬라이드에 맞출 수
we can't fit the whole RNN on the slide
없는 또 다른 실용적인 예는 문자
is this idea of a character level language model.
수준 언어 모델의 아이디어입니다.
And it's really funny because these
10년 전에는 꽤
were shown to be quite effective 10 years ago.
효과적이라는 것이 정말 재미있습니다.
And it's really funny because you
현재의 언어 모델의
can see how the current wave of language models
물결이 RNN으로 문자를 예측하는 이
are a build up of this really simple approach of just
매우 간단한 접근 방식의 축적이라는 것을
predicting characters with RNNs.
볼 수 있어 정말 재미있습니다.
So usually when you do a model like this,
보통 이런 모델을 만들면
you will input your characters, and then people
문자를 입력하고, 이를 원-핫
call this a one hot encoding where you basically have one--
인코딩이라고 부르며, 벡터의 한 위치에 1이 있고
you have a one in your vector and zeros
나머지 위치에는
in every other location.
0이 있습니다.
So it's the index here.
여기서 인덱스입니다.
You can encode this as the index,
이것을 인덱스로 인코딩할 수
and then we can use these as inputs.
있고, 이를 입력으로 사용할 수 있습니다.
And we can calculate our hidden layers
이전 숨겨진 층과
based on the previous hidden layer as well
현재 입력을 기반으로
as the current input.
숨겨진 층을 계산할 수 있습니다.
And then we have our output layer the same
출력층도 동일하게,
where now we can look at, what is
여기서 해당 올바른 값에 대한
the output for the corresponding correct value
출력을 볼 수 있습니다. 이는 다음 시간
here, which is taken as the next time step.
단계로 취해집니다.
So we want the output for example to be e,
예를 들어 출력이 e가 되기를 원하며,
we map it over here we look at--
이를 여기로 매핑하고,
you can imagine this is something like softmax,
소프트맥스와 같은 것을 상상할
and we have the logits, so these are the scores.
수 있으며, 로짓이 있어 점수입니다.
2.2, it's lower than 4.1.
2.2는 4.1보다 낮습니다.
So yeah, we have-- this is maybe not
그래서 네, 이 시간 단계에서 출력이
so great of an output at this time step,
그리 좋지 않을 수
and so on and so forth.
있습니다.
So you can really view this as a time step wise classification
그래서 이를 시간 단계별 분류 문제로 볼 수
And that's exactly what in general, these language models
일반적으로 이러한 언어 모델이 하는 것은
are doing, is time step wise classification based on softmax.
소프트맥스를 기반으로 한 시간 단계별 분류입니다.
So at test time, the basic idea is
테스트 시간에 기본 아이디어는 문자를
we need to also sample characters one at a time
한 번에 하나씩 샘플링하고
and just feed it back into the model,
모델에 다시
so it sees what it generated at the previous time step,
피드하여 이전 시간 단계에서 생성한 것을 보게
so on and so forth, repeating until we generate the words.
하는 것입니다. 이를 반복하여 단어를 생성합니다.
So you can actually create RNNs to do this basic language
문자 수준에서 작동하여 이 기본 언어 모델링 작업을 수행하는 RNN을 실제로
modeling task by operating at a character level,
만들 수 있으며,
and it works quite well.
잘 작동합니다.
One thing to note is that in terms of this input layer,
하나 주목할 점은 이 입력 레이어와 관련하여,
usually we don't actually input one hot embeddings
보통 우리는 모델에 원-핫 임베딩을
into the model, and instead we'll
실제로 입력하지
have something called an embedding layer where
않고, 대신 임베딩 레이어라는 것을
this is essentially just a giant matrix, which is the dimensions.
사용한다는 것입니다. 이는 본질적으로 거대한 행렬입니다.
It's D by D, where D is the number of different inputs
D는 모델에 대한 서로 다른
you have to your model.
입력의 수입니다.
And what you do is you can imagine
당신이 하는 것은 이 행렬 곱셈을
this as a matrix multiply where we grab the first row,
상상할 수 있는데, 여기서 우리는 입력
or in this case, we grab the second row
샘플에 따라 임베딩
of our embedding matrix based on what our input sample is here.
행렬의 첫 번째 행 또는 두 번째 행을 가져옵니다.
And we just use this as a matrix multiply.
그리고 우리는 이것을 행렬 곱셈으로 사용합니다.
This is incorrect, actually, this one
사실 이건 틀렸습니다. 이건 더
should be higher probability, yeah.
높은 확률이어야 합니다.
It's Funny, We've had these slides for quite a few years
재미있게도, 우리는 이 슬라이드를 몇 년
and I guess no one noticed it.
동안 가지고 있었고 아무도 눈치채지 못한 것 같습니다.
Anyway, so we have E here as our target character.
어쨌든, 여기 E가 우리의 목표 문자입니다.
And so in this case, you're correct that the model is
그래서 이 경우, 모델이 실제로 잘못하고 있다는 점에서 당신이
actually getting it wrong, so we will
맞습니다. 우리는 이 시간 단계에
want to penalize it heavy for this time step.
대해 강하게 패널티를 주고 싶습니다.
Yeah, that's a good question.
네, 좋은 질문입니다.
Yeah, so one of the nice things about this implementation
네, 이 구현의 좋은 점 중 하나는 정말
is also it's really simple.
간단하다는 것입니다.
So it's 112 lines of Python code,
파이썬 코드가 112줄이고, 다양한
and you can train these models on a variety of different tasks.
작업에 대해 이러한 모델을 훈련할 수 있습니다.
So this is the pre-LLM era of what you could do.
이것은 당신이 할 수 있었던 사전 LLM 시대입니다.
You can train it on sonnets by William Shakespeare.
윌리엄 셰익스피어의 소네트에 대해 훈련할 수 있습니다.
And as I mentioned, there's a blog post
그리고 제가 언급했듯이, 이
by former instructor of this course, Andrej Karpathy, back
과정의 전 강사인 안드레이 카르파티가 2015년에 쓴
in 2015, which talked about how these RNNs are unreasonably
블로그 포스트가 있습니다. 이 포스트는 RNN이 텍스트 생성에서 얼마나
effective at what they do in generating text.
비합리적으로 효과적인지를 다루고 있습니다.
Yeah?
네?
Could you explain again, why you use an embedding layer?
임베딩 레이어를 사용하는 이유를 다시 설명해 주실 수 있나요?
Yeah, so the basic idea for an embedding layer
네, 임베딩 레이어의 기본 아이디어는
is that generally it's better to have vectors as input
일반적으로 모델에 대한 입력으로 벡터를 사용하는
to our models.
것이 더 낫다는 것입니다.
And you can learn what these embedding layers are too.
그리고 이러한 임베딩 레이어가 무엇인지 배울 수 있습니다.
So we tend to favor spread out weights in general
우리는 일반적으로 이러한 것을 학습할 때 분산된
when we're trying to learn these.
가중치를 선호합니다.
So you can initialize your embedding layer
그래서 임베딩 레이어를
to this very small zero values with something like the Kaiming
Kaiming 초기화와 같은 매우 작은 제로 값으로
initialization, we talked about.
초기화할 수 있습니다.
And then you're just looking at one row of it
그런 다음 입력
at a time as your input vector, rather
벡터로서 한 번에 하나의
than it being a number as input, how
행만 보고, 숫자로 입력하는 대신,
you would have to represent that is basically
기본적으로 많은 제로가 있는
a one with a bunch of zeros and optimization only the embedding
하나로 표현해야 합니다. 최적화는 임베딩이 더 잘
works better.
작동합니다.
So yeah, you can do it in 112 lines of python code, which
그래서 네, 112줄의 파이썬 코드로 할 수
is pretty neat.
있습니다. 꽤 멋지죠.
You can train it on Sonnets by William Shakespeare
윌리엄 셰익스피어의 소네트에 대해 훈련할 수
and it'll actually output reasonable text.
있으며, 실제로 합리적인 텍스트를 출력합니다.
We'll go through some examples.
몇 가지 예를 살펴보겠습니다.
So one of the cool things is you can
재미있는 점 중 하나는 모델을
see as you train the model more, it
더 훈련할수록 점점 더
becomes more and more coherent.
일관성이 생긴다는 것입니다.
So at the beginning, it's basically just gibberish
처음에는 W에 대한 적절한 값을 배우지 못했기
because it hasn't learned proper values for W.
때문에 기본적으로 그냥 의미 없는 말입니다.
And then as you train it more and more, it becomes more
그리고 더 많이 훈련할수록, III 단계처럼
like the stage III, looks like English, at least some
보이게 되고, 적어도 일부 단어는
of the words are there.
영어처럼 보입니다.
And then as you train more, it actually
그리고 더 훈련하면
starts working really well, which
실제로 잘 작동하기
this is I guess was a bit of foreshadowing
시작합니다. 이는 AI 시대에 다가올
for what was to come in the era of AI, which is pretty cool.
것에 대한 약간의 예고편이었던 것 같습니다. 꽤 멋지죠.
You can see full on, it learns things
전체적으로 스타일에 대한 것,
about the style, how you should have someone's name,
누군가의 이름을 어떻게 가져야 하는지, 그리고 그럴듯하게
and how something that seems fairly plausible as you
보이는 것에 대해 배우는 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
have it generating more and more,
더 많이 생성할수록
it starts making less and less sense,
점점 덜 의미가
but it's pretty cool to see.
통하지만, 보는 것은 꽤 멋집니다.
You can train it on code, like I think in this example,
코드에 대해 훈련할 수 있습니다. 이 예에서는 리눅스에서
they trained it on Linux.
훈련했다고 생각합니다.
So there's just the source code for Linux.
리눅스의 소스 코드가 있습니다.
They trained one of these character level RNNs,
이러한 문자 수준 RNN 중 하나를
and you can see it generating C code, which looks pretty good.
훈련했으며, C 코드를 생성하는 것을 볼 수 있습니다. 꽤 좋아 보입니다.
I don't know if this would compile,
이게 컴파일될지는
but it looks reasonable just looking at it.
모르겠지만, 보기에는 합리적으로 보입니다.
And this idea has really taken off over the past few years.
그리고 이 아이디어는 지난 몇 년 동안 정말 인기를 끌었습니다.
So I mean, I'm sure you all know it especially since a lot of you
그러니까, 여러분 모두 아시겠지만, 많은 분들이 컴퓨터 과학이나
work in computer science or coding or your students
코딩 분야에서 일하시거나 이 분야의
in this area, but there's all of these different programming
학생들이기 때문에, 이제는 이러한 언어 모델을
tools now for these language models
위한 다양한 프로그래밍 도구가
that were essentially trained on a similar task
있습니다. 이 모델들은 본질적으로
where they consumed a bunch of this training data
기존 코드의 많은 훈련 데이터를 소비하여 유사한 작업에
that's just existing code, and instead of trying to predict
대해 훈련되었습니다. 다음 문자를 예측하려고
the next character, they're trying
하는 대신, 다음
to predict the next token, which is a group of characters.
토큰, 즉 문자 그룹을 예측하려고 합니다.
And how they define tokens depends on the model,
토큰을 정의하는 방법은 모델에 따라 다르며,
and there's a lot of details we could get into there.
그에 대한 많은 세부 사항이 있습니다.
But at a high level, it's a really similar thing,
하지만 높은 수준에서 보면, 정말
they're just predicting groups of characters
비슷한 작업입니다. 그들은 단지 문자
autoregressively one after the next.
그룹을 순차적으로 예측하고 있습니다.
And it's really seen a blow up in recent years
최근 몇 년 동안 이러한 기존 도구들
with all these existing tools.
덕분에 폭발적으로 증가했습니다.
Yeah?
네?
What is the input to the model?
모델에 대한 입력은 무엇인가요?
Is It like a trigger.
트리거 같은 건가요?
Oh, what like for this?
아, 이거에 대한 건가요?
Yeah.
네.
You could have the input be--
입력을 무작위 문자로
you just-- maybe you start with a random character.
시작할 수 있습니다.
Could be one way to do it, but you
그렇게 하는 방법일 수
would need some initial input.
있지만, 초기 입력이 필요합니다.
There could be-- usually with language models
언어 모델에는 일반적으로 미리
they have a start token as a predetermined.
정해진 시작 토큰이 있습니다.
This is always what you see at the start of your sequence.
이것은 항상 시퀀스의 시작 부분에서 볼 수 있는 것입니다.
So you could do a similar things with RNNs.
그래서 RNN과 비슷한 방식으로 할 수 있습니다.
I don't know in this exact scenario what they did.
이 정확한 시나리오에서 그들이 무엇을 했는지는 모르겠습니다.
Maybe they just did a character, but it's hard to know.
아마도 그들은 단순히 문자를 사용했을 수도 있지만, 알기 어렵습니다.
So the question is, how does labeling
그래서 질문은 언어 모델에서 레이블링은
work with language models?
어떻게 작동하나요?
And the neat thing about these pure language
이 순수 언어 모델의 멋진 점은 그들이 단지
models, all they're doing is just predicting the next token.
다음 토큰을 예측하는 것뿐이라는 것입니다.
You don't need to label it, you just
레이블을 붙일 필요가 없고,
need to give it a lot of text.
많은 텍스트만 제공하면 됩니다.
That's why these models are so good,
이 모델들이 그렇게 좋은 이유는
is because they scrape the internet for essentially all
인터넷에서 본질적으로 모든 사용 가능한 텍스트를 긁어모으고,
available text, and then they train the model on all of it.
그 모든 것에 대해 모델을 훈련시키기 때문입니다.
So that's why they're so good.
그래서 그들이 그렇게 좋은 이유입니다.
It's because it's just generating the next token,
그냥 다음 토큰을 생성하고, 레이블을 붙일
and you don't need to label it.
필요가 없기 때문입니다.
So that's why language models are so good.
그래서 언어 모델이 그렇게 좋은 이유입니다.
So the question is, if we're always
질문은, 매 시간 단계에서
taking the maximum probability output at each time step,
항상 최대 확률 출력을 취한다면, 우리는 항상
we always just be generating the same thing over and over again.
같은 것을 반복해서 생성하게 될 것입니다.
And the answer is yes, actually.
그리고 대답은 실제로 그렇습니다.
So if you just took the maximum probability,
그래서 최대 확률을 취하면, 이 예시는
I guess this example is not so good.
그리 좋지 않습니다.
But imagine the probabilities are correct here
하지만 확률이 여기서 정확하다고 가정하고,
and you just took the maximum probability at each time step.
매 시간 단계에서 최대 확률을 취한다고 상상해 보세요.
You would always be getting the same output
같은 입력에 대해 항상 같은 출력을
given the same input.
얻게 될 것입니다.
In practice what people do, is they
실제로 사람들이 하는 것은,
don't do this is called greedy decoding,
이것은 탐욕적 디코딩이라고 불리며, 항상
you're always picking the maximum probability.
최대 확률을 선택하는 것이 아닙니다.
In practice, they sample based on a distribution,
실제로는, 그들은 소프트맥스에서 출력된
the distribution given by the probabilities output
확률에 의해 주어진 분포를 기반으로
by your softmax.
샘플링합니다.
So you won't pick the max probability,
그래서 최대 확률을
you would pick say in this case probability 0.84 for this one,
선택하지 않고, 이 경우에는 0.84 확률을 선택하거나 다른
or probability 0.13 for this other output variable.
출력 변수에 대해 0.13 확률을 선택합니다.
And then you would run that for each sequence.
그리고 각 시퀀스에 대해 그것을 실행합니다.
And there's a bunch of different ways you can do it too.
그리고 할 수 있는 방법이 여러 가지 있습니다.
You can search ahead.
미리 검색할 수 있습니다.
It's called beam searching, where you're
이것은 빔 검색이라고 불리며,
trying different ones and seeing which
여러 가지를 시도하고 시퀀스에
one has the highest overall probability for the sequence.
대해 전체 확률이 가장 높은 것을 찾는 것입니다.
So there's a lot of-- this is a whole active area of research,
그래서 많은 연구가 진행 중입니다. 이러한 모델에서
how do you sample from these models?
샘플링하는 방법은 무엇인가요?
But the simple answer is you don't always
하지만 간단한 대답은 항상 가장
pick the highest probability.
높은 확률을 선택하지 않는다는 것입니다.
Yeah, so the question is in the case where we have many to one
네, 그래서 질문은 여러 개의 출력이 있는 경우,
outputs, are we outputting something each time
매번 무언가를 출력하는지 아니면
or do we have something to look at here?
여기서 볼 것이 있는지입니다.
So I think in practice to save compute
실제로 계산을 절약하기 위해 사용되지
you wouldn't want to output something that's never used.
않는 것을 출력하고 싶지 않을 것입니다.
But you could feasibly output at each time step.
하지만 각 시간 단계에서 출력할 수 있습니다.
And it might be interesting depending on your problem,
문제에 따라 흥미로울 수 있으며, 훈련
to look at that and understand, is the output converging
과정에서 출력이 수렴하고 있는지 이해하는
over the course of training or not?
것이 중요할 수 있습니다.
Something like that.
그런 것 같습니다.
So it might be useful to look at,
그래서 살펴보는 것이 유용할 수 있지만, 일반적으로
but generally people wouldn't do it just to save compute.
사람들은 계산을 절약하기 위해 그렇게 하지는 않을 것입니다.
But it could be useful, actually yeah.
하지만 실제로 유용할 수 있습니다.
It could help you understand the way your model works.
모델이 작동하는 방식을 이해하는 데 도움이 될 수 있습니다.
If there's certain triggers or things that help
정확한 답을 예측하는 데
it predict the correct answer.
도움이 되는 특정 트리거나 요소가 있을 수 있습니다.
Cool, good questions.
좋은 질문입니다.
So we'll keep on chugging along.
그래서 계속 진행하겠습니다.
We talked about these RNNs, how good they
우리는 이러한 RNN에 대해 이야기했으며, 문자를 생성하는
are at generating characters.
데 얼마나 좋은지에 대해 이야기했습니다.
We related them to some of these modern coding
우리는 그것들을 현대 코딩 도구와
tools, which are really neat.
연결했으며, 정말 멋집니다.
One of the cool things also about RNNs
RNN의 또 다른 멋진 점은
is you can look at the activation values,
활성화 값을 살펴볼 수 있으며, 때때로 모델이
and they'll actually sometimes tell you
추적하는 것에 대해 흥미로운
interesting things about what the model is tracking.
정보를 제공한다는 것입니다.
So in our little toy example, we looked at the output activations
우리의 작은 장난감 예제에서 출력 활성화를 살펴보았고,
, and you would see it's the current value and the previous
현재 값과 이전 값을 볼 수
value.
있습니다.
That was what the RNN states or cells were tracking.
그것이 RNN 상태 또는 셀에서 추적하는 것이었습니다.
What you can also do is give it basically a sequence here.
또한 기본적으로 여기에 시퀀스를 제공할 수 있습니다.
And the models I'll show in these slides,
슬라이드에서 보여줄
it's using a tanh activation, so this is from 1 to minus 1,
모델은 tanh 활성화를 사용하고 있으며, 이는 1에서
and minus 1 means it's visualized as red here, and very
-1까지이며, -1은 여기서 빨간색으로 시각화되고,
close to one would be blue.
1에 가까운 것은 파란색입니다.
We get the whole spectrum here.
여기에서 전체 스펙트럼을 얻습니다.
And you can look at--
각 문자가 들어올 때,
for each character coming in, what
그 시간 단계에서 해당
is the activation of that cell at that time step?
셀의 활성화는 무엇인지 살펴볼 수 있습니다.
And so that's how their color coding these plots here.
그래서 그들이 이 플롯을 색상 코드화하는 방식입니다.
This one's not really showing anything, it's random.
이것은 실제로 아무것도 보여주지 않으며, 무작위입니다.
A lot of them won't be interpretable.
많은 것들이 해석할 수 없을 것입니다.
But some of them have pretty cool things that you can track.
하지만 일부는 추적할 수 있는 꽤 멋진 것들이 있습니다.
For example, this one's a quote detector,
예를 들어, 이것은 인용 탐지기이며,
so it turns on basically as soon as the quote starts
인용이 시작되면 기본적으로
and it ends when the quote ends.
켜지고 인용이 끝나면 꺼집니다.
So this is basically something in the RNN tracking,
그래서 기본적으로 이것은 RNN 추적의 일부로,
we need to have an end quote at some point.
어느 시점에 끝 인용부호가 필요합니다.
And when to put it is something the model
그리고 그것을 언제 넣을지는 모델이 알아내려고
is trying to figure out, but it's tracking it.
하는 것이지만, 추적하고 있습니다.
Another cool thing is the line length tracking cell.
또 다른 멋진 것은 줄 길이 추적 셀입니다.
So it starts very high value.
그래서 매우 높은 값에서 시작합니다.
And then it becomes a very low value as you
그리고 모델이 새 줄 문자가 있을
near where the model thinks there'll
것이라고 생각하는 곳에
be a new line character.
가까워질수록 매우 낮은 값이 됩니다.
So this is also cool as a way to look at this other value.
그래서 이것은 다른 값을 보는 방법으로도 멋집니다.
And these are, again, just single activations
그리고 이것들은 우리가 보고
in a layer of this model that we're looking at, and mapping it
있는 이 모델의 레이어에서 단일 활성화이며,
to each character.
각 문자에 매핑됩니다.
So it's highly interpretable.
그래서 매우 해석 가능합니다.
They have this if statement cell.
그들은 이 if 문 셀을 가지고 있습니다.
So anything within an if statement
그래서 if 문 내의 모든 것이
is being tracked here, which is also pretty cool.
여기에서 추적되고 있으며, 이것도 꽤 멋집니다.
And even things like detecting quotes or comments
그리고 인용부호나 주석을 감지하는 것과 같은
because it needs to know to output the end of comment
것들도 필요합니다. 주석 끝 문자를 출력해야
character here.
하니까요.
So it's something it needs to track.
그래서 이것은 추적해야 할 것입니다.
And so you have this nice interpretable cell as well.
그래서 당신은 이 멋진 해석 가능한 셀도 가지고 있습니다.
And then finally this code depth cell.
그리고 마지막으로 이 코드 깊이 셀입니다.
So as you have nesting in your code,
코드에 중첩이 있을 때,
it activates more and more at each time step,
각 시간 단계마다,
at each not time step, at each step
각 들여쓰기
into the indentation into your code hierarchy.
단계마다 더 많이 활성화됩니다.
So yeah, this is pretty neat.
그래서 네, 이것은 꽤 멋집니다.
You can actually look at the activations
실제로 활성화를 보고 입력에
and directly map them onto the inputs
직접 매핑할 수 있으며,
without needing to do any fancy tricks, which is actually pretty
특별한 트릭이 필요하지 않습니다. 이것은 RNN의 일부
incredible, if you think about how
숨겨진 상태가 얼마나 해석
interpretable some of these hidden states are in the RNN.
가능한지를 생각하면 정말 놀랍습니다.
It's actually somewhat similar to what we were doing where
실제로 우리가 수동으로 할당하던
we were manually assigning it.
것과 다소 유사합니다.
But the RNN is internally doing a very similar process.
하지만 RNN은 내부적으로 매우 유사한 과정을 수행하고 있습니다.
Cool, so I'll talk about now some of the trade
좋습니다, 이제 RNN을 사용하고
offs why you might want to use an RNN, when is it helpful.
싶을 때의 트레이드오프에 대해 이야기하겠습니다.
So the nice thing is they can process any length of input.
좋은 점은 어떤 길이의 입력도 처리할 수 있다는 것입니다.
So a lot of these modern language models
그래서 현대의 많은 언어 모델은
that rely on transformers have something
변환기에 의존하며,
called a context length or context window, maximum context
최대 컨텍스트 길이 또는 컨텍스트 창이라고
window.
하는 것이 있습니다.
RNNs don't have this.
RNN은 이것이 없습니다.
They can just take a sequence of infinite length,
본질적으로 무한 길이의 시퀀스를 받아들일 수
essentially, as long as you can keep running the model on it.
있습니다. 모델을 계속 실행할 수 있는 한 말이죠.
So there's no context length limit.
그래서 컨텍스트 길이 제한이 없습니다.
The computation for the time step, t
시간 단계 t에 대한 계산은 이론적으로 숨겨진 상태에
can, in theory, use information from many steps
캡처된 경우 여러 단계
back if it's captured in the hidden state.
뒤의 정보를 사용할 수 있습니다.
So if your model is effectively capturing
모델이 입력 시퀀스의 모든 동적을
all of the dynamics of your input
숨겨진 상태에서 효과적으로
sequence in the hidden state, in theory
캡처하고 있다면, 이론적으로
it can use values from an extremely long time ago.
매우 오래된 값도 사용할 수 있습니다.
But in practice, there might be some issues
하지만 실제로는 이와 관련된 몇 가지
with this, which we'll go into some details there.
문제가 있을 수 있으며, 그에 대한 세부 사항을 다룰 것입니다.
Also, the model size does not increase for a longer input.
또한, 모델 크기는 더 긴 입력에 대해 증가하지 않습니다.
So we had an example where, what if you just
그래서 각 입력 시간 단계마다
had a different layer for each input time step?
다른 레이어가 있다고 가정해 보겠습니다.
You don't have this issue, which is nice.
이 문제는 없으므로 좋습니다.
And then we're applying the same weights at each time step.
그리고 각 시간 단계에서 동일한 가중치를 적용하고 있습니다.
So basically, we know the update rule
기본적으로, 출력을 계산하는 업데이트
for how we calculate the outputs is the same every single time.
규칙은 매번 동일하다는 것을 알고 있습니다.
So there's some nice symmetry here.
여기에는 멋진 대칭성이 있습니다.
And also, just when you think conceptually about the problem,
문제를 개념적으로 생각할 때, 매
you're always doing the same thing
시간
at every single time step, which is nice conceptually
단계마다 항상 같은 작업을 수행하는데,
and also helps with some implementation as well.
이는 개념적으로 좋고 구현에도 도움이 됩니다.
So what are the main disadvantages?
주요 단점은 무엇인가요?
So you need to compute the previous hidden state to compute
다음 숨겨진 상태를 계산하기 위해 매번 이전 숨겨진
the next one every single time.
상태를 계산해야 합니다.
So this can be slow if you need to.
필요하다면 느릴 수 있습니다.
Each hidden state is determined and is conditioned
각 숨겨진 상태는 이전 상태들에
on all the previous ones, then this recurrence computation
의존하여 결정되므로, 이 재귀 계산은 실제로
can actually end up taking a lot of time.
많은 시간을 소모할 수 있습니다.
So although this is not an issue during inference time
추론 시간에는 문제가
when you're always-- like for a transformer,
되지 않지만,
also you have this issue where you
훈련
need to output the next token or character every single time,
시간에는 손실을 계산하기
but at training time, it's actually
위해 이전
difficult to batch all of these together and during training
숨겨진 상태를 계산해야 하므로
because in order to calculate the loss,
모든 것을
you need to calculate the previous hidden states.
배치하기가 어렵습니다.
So this can pose challenges for scaling up to a lot of data.
이는 많은 데이터로 확장하는 데 어려움을 초래할 수 있습니다.
And then in practice, it's actually
실제로는 고정 크기의 숨겨진
difficult to access information many time steps back
상태를 가지고 있기 때문에
because we have a fixed size hidden state,
여러 시간 단계 뒤의
and we're trying to cram all the information into it.
정보를 접근하기가 어렵습니다.
So you'll eventually lose some information
따라서 시퀀스가 길어질수록
as your sequence goes longer and longer.
일부 정보를 잃게 됩니다.
Cool, I'll talk about some applications more specific
좋습니다, RNN이 성공을 거둔 컴퓨터 비전과
to computer vision, where RNNs have seen success now.
관련된 몇 가지 응용 프로그램에 대해 이야기하겠습니다.
So one of them is image captioning,
그 중 하나는 우리가 이야기한 이미지
which we talked about.
캡셔닝입니다.
So the basic thing here is we mentioned
여기서 기본적인 것은 시퀀스를
there's this start token or start character which
시작하는 시작 토큰 또는 시작 문자가
begins the sequence.
있다는 것입니다.
And then you will terminate when you have this end character
그리고 종료 문자나 종료 토큰이 있을
or end token.
때 종료됩니다.
In this case, it seems like it's word level tokens.
이 경우, 단어 수준의 토큰처럼 보입니다.
So you could have a model like this.
이런 모델을 가질 수 있습니다.
The most basic way to do it is you
가장 기본적인 방법은
essentially have a CNN or something that encodes,
본질적으로 이미지를 인코딩하는 시각적
a visual encoder, that encodes the image,
인코더인 CNN을 가지고, 이를
and we use that as input to our recurrent neural network
우리의 순환 신경망에 입력으로 사용하고 이전에
as well as the previous text that was generated.
생성된 텍스트와 함께 사용하는 것입니다.
So we have two stages here.
여기에는 두 단계가 있습니다.
And very more concretely, how would you
그리고 CNN과 RNN을 어떻게 결합할 것인지
combine the CNN and RNN?
더 구체적으로 설명하겠습니다.
You can imagine you have this test image.
테스트 이미지를 상상해 보세요.
It comes in, so your model's going downwards here,
이미지가 들어오면, 모델은 위쪽의 첫 번째
starting at the first layers at the top
레이어에서 시작하여
and then moving downwards.
아래로 내려갑니다.
You can imagine this is something that was trained
이것은 ImageNet에서 훈련된
on ImageNet or something.
것이라고 상상할 수 있습니다.
And so we're not going to use the class labels,
클래스 레이블은 사용하지 않지만, 마지막에서
but we're going to use this second to last layer.
두 번째 레이어를 사용할 것입니다.
This is the common strategy we saw
이는 전이 학습에서 본
for transfer learning as well, or this
일반적인 전략이며,
getting good visual representations of images.
이미지의 좋은 시각적 표현을 얻는 방법입니다.
So we use the second to last layer.
따라서 마지막에서 두 번째 레이어를 사용합니다.
And then we can start using this as input to our hidden state.
그리고 이제 이것을 우리의 숨겨진 상태에 대한 입력으로 사용할 수 있습니다.
And now our hidden state is also a function
이제 우리의 숨겨진
of this Wih value here.
상태는 이 Wih 값의 함수이기도 합니다.
So we don't necessarily have just a hidden state,
단순히 숨겨진 상태만 있는 것이 아니라, 여기서
we're also tracking the visual components here.
시각적 요소도 추적하고 있습니다.
But I won't spend too much time on this
하지만 이는 과제에
because this won't be in any of the assignments,
포함되지 않으므로 너무 많은 시간을
but just to give you a flavor of here's
할애하지 않겠습니다.
how RNNs were used historically with CNNs,
RNN이 역사적으로
where we're taking a CNN pre-trained on ImageNet,
CNN과 함께 어떻게
and now we're including this information
사용되었는지에 대한
into the hidden state as well.
감을 주기 위해서입니다.
So we use the sampling process, either greedy sampling,
우리는 샘플링 프로세스를 사용하여
some other version of sampling to calculate
각 시간 단계에서
the tokens at each time step.
토큰을 계산합니다.
We end it when we have this end token.
우리는 종료 토큰이 있을 때 종료합니다.
Whenever we sample the end token,
종료 토큰을 샘플링할 때마다, 우리는
that's how we know when to finish.
언제 끝내야 하는지를 알 수 있습니다.
And these models actually worked very well for the time.
그리고 이 모델들은 당시 매우 잘 작동했습니다.
I think they had a lot of great successes.
그들은 많은 훌륭한 성공을 거두었다고 생각합니다.
So you can see here a lot of nice examples of where
여기에서 모델이 입력 이미지에 기반하여
the model's outputting very reasonable captions based
매우 합리적인 캡션을 출력하는 많은
on the input image, but also they the models would struggle
좋은 예를 볼 수 있지만, 모델이 많은 시나리오에서 어려움을
in a lot of scenarios too.
겪기도 했습니다.
So a lot of these have to do with the distribution of where
이러한 많은 문제는 훈련 데이터에서 이러한 이미지가 일반적으로
these images are commonly seen in the training data.
나타나는 분포와 관련이 있습니다.
For example, someone holding something with their hands
예를 들어, 누군가가 이렇게 손을 모아 무언가를
cupped like this very much looks how they might hold a mouse.
들고 있는 모습은 마우스를 잡는 모습과 매우 유사합니다.
But obviously, we can tell this is a phone because it's
하지만 분명히 그들이 들고 있는 것은 평평한 물체이므로 이것이 전화기라는 것을
a flat object they're holding, and their hand is facing up,
알 수 있으며, 그들의 손은 아래가 아니라
not downwards.
위를 향하고 있습니다.
So this thing is interesting to see.
이것은 흥미롭게 보입니다.
Also, I guess they think the woman's holding
또한, 그들은 여성이 털
a cat where she's just wearing some fur clothing.
옷을 입고 있는 모습에서 고양이를 들고 있다고 생각하는 것 같습니다.
They see a beach, so they assume there's a surfboard.
그들은 해변을 보고 서핑 보드가 있다고 가정합니다.
This type of hallucination, I would say,
이런 종류의 환각은 오늘날
is still extremely common with vision language models
비전 언어 모델에서 여전히 매우
today, where it'll think there's objects present that
흔하며, 특정 장면에서 일반적으로 존재하는 물체가 있다고
are commonly present in a given scene,
생각하지만, 당신이
but aren't in this particular scene that you're looking at.
보고 있는 특정 장면에는 존재하지 않습니다.
Also, things like bird being perched in a tree
또한, 나무에 앉아 있는 새나 공을 던지는
or throwing a ball, but he's catching a ball.
것과 같은 것들이 있지만, 그는 공을 잡고 있습니다.
These are all based on the bias in the data set, essentially,
이 모든 것은 본질적으로 데이터 세트의 편향에 기반하고
and the model learning that during training, it
있으며, 모델이 훈련 중에 이를 학습하면서 실제
is most probably true that a certain object
이미지에서는 그렇지 않은 경우에도
or a certain action is being performed
특정 물체나 특정 행동이
when in the actual image it's not the case.
수행되고 있다고 가장 가능성이 높다고 학습합니다.
So in the data set, there's high co-occurrence
따라서 데이터 세트에서는 이러한 행동이나 물체가 특정 장면과
of these actions or objects with the particular scene.
높은 동시 발생을 보입니다.
So the model learns to associate them,
모델은 이를 연관 짓는 법을 배우지만,
but it doesn't learn to disentangle.
이를 분리하는 법은 배우지 않습니다.
It's happening in this scene because of the-- in this scene,
이 장면에서 발생하는 이유는-- 이 장면에서는
we know they're not throwing because the glove is here,
장갑이 여기 있고, 공이 장갑으로 들어가고
and the ball is going into the glove, not on the other hand,
있으므로 던지고 있지 않다는 것을 알고
but you need to explain it like that.
있지만, 그렇게 설명해야 합니다.
And the way we train these models,
그리고 이러한 모델을 훈련하는
we're training them just to output the caption.
방식은 캡션을 출력하도록 훈련하는 것입니다.
So we're not doing any explanation there,
그래서 우리는 거기서 어떤
and that's why it's part of the reason you
설명도 하지 않으며, 이것이
see this co-occurrence issue.
이러한 동시 발생 문제를 보는 이유 중 하나입니다.
So for visual question answering,
비주얼 질문 응답을 위해, 이는 RNN이 사용된
this is another really common task where RNNs were used,
또 다른 매우 일반적인 작업이며,
and there are two formulations for visual question answering
비주얼 질문 응답에 대해 일반적으로 사용된 두
that were commonly used.
가지 공식이 있습니다.
One is to basically, you say you have
하나는 기본적으로 캡션 모델이 있다고
a model that is a captioning model,
말하고, 그것이 질문에 얼마나
and you want to see how well it could answer questions.
잘 대답할 수 있는지를 보고 싶어하는 것입니다.
One thing you could do is to give it this question,
할 수 있는 한 가지는 이 질문을 주고,
and then have it output text and look
텍스트를 출력하게 한
at the probabilities of each of the answer sequences.
다음 각 답변 시퀀스의 확률을 살펴보는 것입니다.
So you have a probability for each character or token,
그래서 각 문자나 토큰에 대한 확률이
and you could multiply them together
있으며, 이를 곱하여 전체
to get the probability of the overall answer.
답변의 확률을 얻을 수 있습니다.
This is one way you could use one of these RNN style models
이것은 이러한 RNN 스타일 모델 중 하나를 사용하여 질문 응답을
to do question answering.
수행하는 한 가지 방법입니다.
A more common way people did it is they would have basically
사람들이 더 일반적으로 사용한 방법은 기본적으로 모델에
a question as input to the model,
대한 입력으로 질문을 주고, 여러 다른 답변을
multiple different answers also as
모델에 대한 별도의 입력으로
separate inputs to your model.
주는 것입니다.
And then it's outputting essentially a probability
그런 다음 본질적으로 질문당 확률을
per question.
출력합니다.
So in this case, it would be a four way classifier where
이 경우, 네 가지 클래스가 있는 네 방향 분류기가 되어,
you have four different classes: answer 1, answer 2, answer 3,
답변 1, 답변 2, 답변 3, 답변 4가
answer 4, and you're just outputting the probabilities.
있으며, 확률을 출력하는 것입니다.
And a lot of different ways you can formulate it,
형식화할 수 있는 다양한 방법이
but this is a very common task in computer vision
있지만, 이는 언어를 사용해야 하고 시퀀스
where you need to use language and where
모델링이 도움이 되는
sequence modeling helps.
컴퓨터 비전에서 매우 일반적인 작업입니다.
Also visual dialogue.
또한 비주얼 대화.
At the time, these were all considered very separate tasks.
당시에는 이 모든 것이 매우 별개의 작업으로 간주되었습니다.
These days, the tasks you have one model that can do almost all
요즘에는 거의 모든 작업을 수행할 수 있는 하나의
of these, but how can you have a chat about an image?
모델이 있지만, 이미지에 대해 어떻게 대화할 수 있을까요?
We've really seen an explosion in the capabilities
지난 2년 동안 이러한 종류의
of these kinds of models in the last two years.
모델의 능력이 폭발적으로 증가하는 것을 보았습니다.
Maybe one other type of model that RNNs were commonly used for
RNN이 일반적으로 사용된 또 다른 유형의 모델은 이 비주얼
is for this visual navigation task.
내비게이션 작업을 위한 것입니다.
So you have these images coming in, and you want to output
그래서 여러분은 이러한 이미지가 들어오고, 2D
a sequence of directions to move in some 2D floor plan.
평면에서 이동할 방향의 시퀀스를 출력하고 싶어합니다.
How do you get to the target destination?
목표 목적지에 어떻게 도달하나요?
There's another application for you
이 시퀀스
all to be aware of where these sequence models were used.
모델이 사용된 또 다른 응용 프로그램이 있으니 알아두세요.
One thing I want to note that I didn't really explicitly mention
제가 이전에 명시적으로 언급하지 않았던 한 가지는,
before, but just in the same way where
다층 CNN이나 다층 밀집
we can have multi-layer CNNs or multi-layer of these dense
또는 완전 연결 계층을 가질 수 있는 것과 같은 방식으로, 다층
or fully connected layers, you can also have multi-layer RNNs.
RNN도 가질 수 있다는 점입니다.
And in practice, most of the RNNs,
실제로 제가 보여준 대부분의
I showed were multi-layer RNNs.
RNN은 다층 RNN이었습니다.
Now, the main difference is that you treat each layer separately.
주요 차이점은 각 층을 별도로 처리한다는 것입니다.
So the hidden state of say layer 1,
예를 들어, 1층의 은닉 상태는 1층의
depends on the hidden state of the previous time
이전 시간 단계의
step of layer 1.
은닉 상태에 의존합니다.
So in this of depth wise dimension--
깊이 방향 차원에서는,
I'm sorry in the depth dimension, each of these layers,
각 층에서 이전 시간 단계의 은닉
you're only looking at the hidden states
상태만을
from that layer in the previous time steps.
보고 있습니다.
And then in terms of looking at Windows in the time dimension,
그리고 시간 차원에서 윈도우를 보는 측면에서, 첫 번째
instead of-- so the first layer will have the actual input
층은 실제 입력 x를 입력으로
x as the input, but then the second layer
가지지만, 두 번째
will take as input the output y from the previous layer.
층은 이전 층의 출력 y를 입력으로 사용합니다.
So you can stack these up, and it
이렇게 쌓을 수 있으며,
forms this grid, where each layer is operating with regards
각 층은 그 층의 이전 은닉 상태에 대해서만
to the previous hidden states only within that layer,
작동하지만, 층 간의
but then in terms of passing input output that
입력 출력 전달도
is between layers.
있습니다.
And so you can see to calculate this top right value
따라서 이 오른쪽 상단 값을 계산하기
we need to calculate all of the different values, all
위해서는 이 전체 계산 그래프의 다양한 값,
of the different hidden states in this entire computational
다양한 은닉 상태를 미리
graph beforehand.
계산해야 합니다.
So you can get a feel for how as you start training,
그래서 훈련을 시작하면 이 과정이
this gets to be a very involved process and not very efficient.
매우 복잡해지고 비효율적이라는 느낌을 받을 수 있습니다.
OK, I'll talk about one of the key variants for RNNs that was
좋습니다, 제가 1990년대에 실제로 제안된 RNN의 주요
proposed actually a while ago in the 1990s,
변형 중 하나에 대해 이야기하겠습니다.
but saw a lot of success for quite some time until
이 변형은 LSTM이라고 하며, 변환기 혁명
the transformer revolution called LSTMs.
이전에 상당한 성공을 거두었습니다.
You won't need to know about the details of how LSTMs operate,
LSTM의 작동 방식에 대한 세부 사항을 알
but what I hope you learned is that RNNs have
필요는 없지만, RNN이 LSTM이
some key disadvantages that LSTMs seek to alleviate,
완화하려고 하는 몇 가지 주요 단점이 있다는 것을
and a lot of the more modern state space
배우기를 바랍니다. 많은 현대
models also try to seek to alleviate
상태 공간 모델도 RNN이
some of these same issues that RNNs face.
직면하는 동일한 문제를 완화하려고 합니다.
So we talked about how by default, tanh
기본적으로 tanh가 정말 일반적으로 사용되는
is a really commonly used activation function.
활성화 함수라는 것을 이야기했습니다.
And we also talked about how you have this Whh
그리고 이전 은닉 상태를
matrix that converts your previous hidden state
새로운 상태로 변환하는 Whh
to the new one.
행렬이 있다는 것도 이야기했습니다.
And it's summed with this Wxh matrix that converts your input
이것은 현재 시간 단계에서 입력 벡터 xt를
vector xt at the current time step
은닉 상태 차원으로
into your hidden state dimension and then you sum these together.
변환하는 Wxh 행렬과 합산됩니다.
You can also formulate this as we have our weights here,
이것을 이렇게 벡터를 쌓는 것으로
and you're stacking the vectors like this.
공식화할 수도 있습니다.
And so sometimes for shorthand people,
그래서 사람들은 때때로
we'll just combine both of these W's together to form one big W.
이 두 개의 W를 결합하여 하나의 큰 W를 형성합니다.
But you should note that these are two blocks that
하지만 이 두 블록은 대각선으로 배치되어 있다는 점에 유의해야
are diagonally positioned together
합니다. 이렇게 공식화하면 W에
where there would be like-- if you're formulating like this,
많은 0이 존재합니다. 왜냐하면
there's a lot of zeros in this W,
Whh는 xt와 전혀
because Whh is not interacting with xt at all,
상호작용하지 않기 때문입니다. 하지만 이것은
but this is a shorthand way to notate it
생각하고 수학을 기록하는
where it makes thinking about it and writing down
것을 쉽게 하기 위한 약식
the math easier.
표기법입니다.
So you will see all three variants here.
그래서 여기서 세 가지 변형을 모두 볼 수 있습니다.
This one's maybe the most explicit
이것은 실제 값, 비영
about where the actual values, the non-zero values,
값 및 가중치 행렬이 어디에 있는지 가장
and the weight matrices lie.
명시적일 수 있습니다.
And so one way to think of it is you stack these vectors
그래서 이것을 생각하는 한 가지 방법은 이러한
together, which is shown here.
벡터를 함께 쌓는 것입니다.
We're multiplying by this W and then we pass it through tanh h.
우리는 이 W로 곱하고 tanh h를 통과시킵니다.
This gives us our output h,t which we pass to the next RNN.
이것은 다음 RNN에 전달하는 출력 h,t를 제공합니다.
You can imagine these are stacked.
이것들이 쌓여 있다고 상상할 수 있습니다.
And then you may also have either the output directly yt,
그리고 출력 yt를 직접 가질 수도
or we have this layer where it's a weight matrix times
있고, ht에 가중치 행렬을 곱한 후 활성화 함수가
ht with the activation function around it too.
있는 층을 가질 수도 있습니다.
Yeah, question.
네, 질문입니다.
Oh sure.
아, 물론입니다.
So here we have multilayer RNNs, how is the [INAUDIBLE] matrix
여기 다층 RNN이 있는데, [INAUDIBLE] 행렬은 거의
pretty much [INAUDIBLE]?
[INAUDIBLE]인가요?
Yeah so the weights are shared within the layers
네, 다층 RNN의 경우 가중치는 층
for multi-layer RNN.
내에서 공유됩니다.
So all of these hidden state updates
따라서 모든 은닉 상태 업데이트는 동일한
will use the same weights.
가중치를 사용합니다.
And then each layer, which you stack it vertically
그리고 이 다이어그램에서 수직으로
in this diagram, each layer will have a separate set of weights.
쌓인 각 층은 별도의 가중치 집합을 가집니다.
OK, yeah, so this is the way that it works.
알겠어요, 그래서 이게 작동하는 방식입니다.
And then when you have backpropagation,
그리고 역전파가 있을 때, 우리가
we talked about.
이야기했던 것입니다.
If you don't have a loss for each time step,
각 시간 단계에 대한 손실이 없다면,
why you need to only calculate your loss based on what
왜 출력 h,t의 손실을 기반으로
the losses of your output h,t, and so when you do this
손실을 계산해야 하는지, 그래서 이
backpropagation, you're multiplying by W,
역전파를 수행할 때 W로 곱하고
and then you're also taking the derivative of tanh.
tanh의 미분도 취합니다.
And both of these can actually have some issues.
이 두 가지 모두 실제로 문제가 있을 수 있습니다.
So when specifically mathematically
특히 수학적으로 우리의 숨겨진
looking at what is the gradient of how--
상태 t의 각 구성 요소를
if we change each component of our hidden state t,
h,t-1에 대해 변경할 때의 기울기를
with respect to h,t minus 1.
살펴보면.
Sorry, if we change each component of h,t minus 1,
죄송합니다, h,t-1의 각 구성 요소를
how will that affect h,t?
변경하면 h,t에 어떤 영향을 미칠까요?
This is what this gradient is calculating.
이 기울기가 계산하는 것입니다.
We need the derivative of tanh because this is our activation
tanh의 미분이 필요합니다. 왜냐하면 이것이 우리의 활성화 함수이기
function.
때문입니다.
And then we have Whh which is the multiply here for converting
그리고 이전 숨겨진 상태를 다음 상태로 변환하기 위해
the previous hidden state to the next one.
여기에서 곱하는 Whh가 있습니다.
So this is actually how we calculate the gradient.
그래서 이것이 실제로 기울기를 계산하는 방법입니다.
And here we can run into issues.
여기에서 문제에 직면할 수 있습니다.
So if we're calculating the loss at each time step,
각 시간 단계에서 손실을 계산하고, 여기에서
and we have lost here the total loss
총 손실을 각
we just summit for each of the weights.
가중치에 대해 합산합니다.
So the total loss is just the sum
총 손실은 이
of the loss at each time step with respect
재사용된 W 행렬에
to this reused W matrix.
대해 각 시간 단계의 손실의 합입니다.
And so you end up getting this product of these dl--
그래서 L,t에 대한 최종 단계에서 L의
to calculate the loss of L-- at the final step L,t with respect
손실을 계산하기 위해, 각 중간 숨겨진 상태와
to h,t, you need to calculate each of the intermediate hidden
그것이 W에 미치는 영향을 계산해야
states and how that affects W in order to calculate this final
이 최종 손실을 체인 룰을 사용하여
loss here by using the chain rule.
계산할 수 있습니다.
We mentioned example here, and just
여기에서 예를 언급했으며, 이것이
to point out why this is an issue.
문제인 이유를 지적하고자 합니다.
If we look at these individual terms,
이 개별 항목을
so if we hone in on this aspect of how
살펴보면, 현재 숨겨진
does changing the current hidden state change the next one, which
상태를 변경하는 것이 다음 상태에
is the majority of these calculations contained
어떻게 영향을 미치는지에 대한
in this product term here, we get
이 측면에 집중하면,
that it's the same thing we mentioned earlier
이 곱셈 항에 포함된 계산의
where you have this derivative of tanh multiplied by your Whh.
대부분과 동일한 것을 언급했던 것입니다.
And so why is this an issue?
그래서 이것이 문제인 이유는 무엇인가요?
Well, first of all, this is the derivative of tanh plotted here.
우선, 이것은 여기에서 플롯된 tanh의 미분입니다.
The maximum value is 1, and so almost always you're
최대 값은 1이며, 거의 항상
getting less than 1.
1보다 작습니다.
So you can have vanishing gradients from this term here.
그래서 이 항에서 소실 기울기가 발생할 수 있습니다.
But even if we assume there's no non-linearity or we
하지만 비선형성이 없다고 가정하거나 이 문제가
pick some other activation function
없는 다른 활성화 함수를
that doesn't have this issue.
선택하더라도.
If we look at this weight matrix here,
각 시간 단계에서 곱하는 이 가중치
that we're multiplying at each time step,
행렬을 살펴보면, 큰 특이값이
either we're going to have a large singular value,
있을 것이고, 그래서
so this will be as the vectors are coming in,
벡터가 들어올 때 최대한 늘어나는 정도가
what is the maximum they'll be stretched?
무엇인지 알 수 있습니다.
If it's say a unit vector singular value is telling you
단위 벡터의 특이값이 행렬에 의해
what's the maximum that a unit vector could
얼마나 늘어날 수
be stretched by the matrix?
있는지를 알려줍니다.
So if it's very large you can have these gradients explode
그래서 만약 매우 크면 기울기가 폭발할
or if it's very small, you can have this vanishing gradients
수 있고, 매우 작으면 소실 기울기
issue.
문제가 발생할 수 있습니다.
And if you have exploding gradients,
폭발하는 기울기가 있다면, 이를
we have a fix which is this scaling the gradient.
해결하는 방법은 기울기를 스케일링하는 것입니다.
So you can just divide or clip it and somehow so that you
그래서 그냥 나누거나 클립하여 너무 큰 기울기가
don't--
문제
so too big of a gradient, it's not too much of an issue.
되지 않도록 할 수 있습니다.
But this really small vanishing gradient issue
하지만 이 정말 작은 소실 기울기
is actually the main issue with why people don't just
문제는 사람들이 실제로 긴
use really long RNNs in practice because of tanh,
RNN을 사용하지 않는 주된 이유입니다.
and because under many scenarios,
tanh 때문이고,
your weight matrix has this property where
많은 시나리오에서 가중치
it's either expanding your activations or reducing them.
행렬이 활성화를 확장하거나 줄이는 특성을 가지고 있기 때문입니다.
So yeah, I think these are the main reasons why it motivated
그래서 네, 이것들이 RNN 아키텍처의 변화를 촉진한 주된
a change in RNN architectures, and why a lot of the reasons why
이유이며, 사람들이 RNN을 사용하지
people don't use RNNs.
않는 이유입니다.
This is one of the main issues.
이것이 주요 문제 중 하나입니다.
So how do you resolve this.
그렇다면 이를 어떻게 해결할까요?
So the way that people did it was this creation of the LSTM.
사람들이 이를 해결한 방법은 LSTM을 만드는 것이었습니다.
And the high level idea, which I won't go into too many details
고수준 아이디어는 여러 가지
because it's actually quite complicated
복잡한 세부 사항이 있지만,
is that you have four of these different gates that
서로 다른 값을 추적하는 네 가지
are tracking different values, that instead
게이트가 있다는 것입니다.
of just having one hidden state, you
단일 은닉 상태 대신
have multiple of these values.
여러 값을 갖습니다.
You precompute to determine how to change your hidden state,
은닉 상태를 변경하는 방법과 다른
and then also what information to pass
경로를 통해 전달할 정보를
through a different pathway.
미리 계산합니다.
So you have the regular hidden state pathway.
정상적인 은닉 상태 경로가 있습니다.
You have a different pathway where it's easier
정보를 전달하기 쉬운
to pass information.
다른 경로가 있습니다.
And this is the basic idea, at a high level they call it a gate
이것이 기본 아이디어이며, 고수준에서 게이트라고 부르거나 셀의 은닉
or what are you actually writing to the hidden state of the cell.
상태에 실제로 무엇을 기록하는지를 나타냅니다.
The input gate, which is deciding whether or not you
입력 게이트는 셀에 정보를 기록할지
write information to the cell.
여부를 결정합니다.
The forget gate, how much to forget from previous time
망각 게이트는 이전 시간 단계에서 얼마나
steps, as well as the output gate, which is how much
잊을지를 결정하며, 출력 게이트는 은닉 상태에
are you actually outputting for your hidden state.
대해 실제로 얼마나 출력하는지를 나타냅니다.
So you can see, this is really involved,
이것은 정말 복잡하며, 많은
a lot of design choices here.
설계 선택이 포함되어 있습니다.
and they put it all together into this, I would say,
그들은 이것을 모두 모아 꽤 복잡한 다이어그램을
fairly complicated diagram, but the basic idea
만들었지만, 기본 아이디어는
is this part is the same where we're
이 부분이 동일하여 가중치 곱셈을
doing this weight multiply.
수행한다는 것입니다.
But now we have four different values we're computing instead
이제 h,t 대신 네 가지
of just the h,t.
다른 값을 계산하고 있습니다.
We have the input gate, and the gate
입력 게이트와 여기에 얼마나
to determine how much to write here,
기록할지를 결정하는 게이트가
and we have our output that's passed to the next hidden state.
있으며, 다음 은닉 상태로 전달되는 출력이 있습니다.
You can think of this top section
여기 위쪽 섹션을 고속도로로 생각할
here as a highway where the goal is to not
수 있으며, 목표는 활성화 함수가
have any activation functions.
없도록 하는 것입니다.
So no tanh.
따라서 tanh가 없습니다.
So we avoid the issues we had where
tanh가 기울기를 소실하게
tanh made the gradients vanish, and all we're applying
만든 문제를 피할 수 있으며, 우리가 적용하는 것은 이 망각
is this forget gate.
게이트뿐입니다.
So as long as we're not basically
각 시간 단계에서 모든 정보를
forgetting all the information at each time step,
기본적으로 잊지 않는 한, 정보를 더
we're able to pass information more easily.
쉽게 전달할 수 있습니다.
This is the high level explanation.
이것이 고수준 설명입니다.
And then more importantly, in practice,
그리고 더 중요한 것은, 실제로
people seem to see that this worked very well.
사람들은 이것이 매우 잘 작동한다는 것을 알게 되는 것 같습니다.
Again, you won't be implementing this for the course at all,
다시 말하지만, 여러분은 이 과정을 위해 이것을 전혀 구현하지 않을
but I think this is a really commonly used baseline still
것이지만, 이것은 여전히 매우 일반적으로 사용되는
and some deep learning papers.
기준선이며 일부 딥러닝 논문에서도 사용됩니다.
So it's good to know about.
그래서 이것에 대해 아는 것이 좋습니다.
But I think you can think of this through the lens of people
하지만 저는 사람들이 RNN이 가지고 있던
are trying to construct these things to make up
모든 문제, 즉 소실 기울기와
for all the issues that RNNs had,
정보 포착 부족을
which is vanishing gradients and also the lack of information
보완하기 위해 이러한 것들을 구성하려고 한다고 생각할
being captured.
수 있습니다.
You need to cram everything into this hidden state.
모든 것을 이 숨겨진 상태에 집어넣어야 합니다.
So you have really long term dependencies.
그래서 정말 긴 의존성이 있습니다.
Those are lost.
그것들은 잃어버립니다.
So they created a separate pathway
그래서 그들은 여기
to pass over this more long term information through the top
위쪽에서 더 긴 정보가 전달될 수 있는
here.
별도의 경로를 만들었습니다.
So do LSTMs solve the vanishing gradient problem completely?
그렇다면 LSTM이 소실 기울기 문제를 완전히 해결합니까?
It definitely helps.
확실히 도움이 됩니다.
So it makes the RNN easier to preserve
그래서 이 상단 경로 다이어그램을 사용하여
this information over many time steps
여러 시간 단계에 걸쳐 이
by using this top pathway diagram.
정보를 보존하는 것이 RNN을 더 쉽게 만듭니다.
So it's in contrast--
그래서 대조적으로, 바닐라 RNN이
it's much harder for Vanilla RNNs
매 시간 단계마다 숨겨진
to learn our current weight matrix that preserves info
상태에서 정보를 보존하는 현재 가중치 행렬을 학습하는
in the hidden state across every single time step,
것은 훨씬 더 어렵습니다.
if we're always doing the same operation,
항상 같은 작업을 수행하고
and we're not able to just pass information directly
활성화 함수 없이 정보를
without an activation function.
직접 전달할 수 없기 때문입니다.
So it doesn't guarantee it, but it makes it significantly easier
그래서 그것을 보장하지는 않지만, 훨씬 더 쉽게 만들고
and it helps improve learning long term dependencies and works
장기 의존성을 학습하는 데 도움이 되며 경험적으로
very well empirically.
매우 잘 작동합니다.
So people generally don't train RNNs so much, and more often
그래서 사람들은 일반적으로 RNN을 많이 훈련하지 않고,
train LSTMs, if you were going to go
이 순환 모델링 경로를
with this recurrent modeling route, but I think in general,
선택할 경우 LSTM을 더 자주 훈련합니다. 하지만 일반적으로 이들은 또한-- 제가
these are also--
말했듯이,
I was saying, I would say significantly fallen out
상당히 유행에서 벗어났다고 말할 수
of fashion, but it gives you a sense
있지만, 사람들이 직면한
of the way that people have tried to design RNNs to account
문제를 설명하기 위해 RNN을 설계하려고 시도한
for the issues they face.
방식을 이해하는 데 도움이 됩니다.
So one other thing that would be cool to tie-in to something
그래서 이 과정에서 이전에 배운 것과 연결할 수 있는 또
you learned earlier in this course,
다른 흥미로운
is this idea of directly adding outputs and skipping
점은, 출력을 직접 추가하고 일부 활성화 함수나
some activation functions or other layers
다른 레이어를 건너뛰는
is actually highly related to the idea
아이디어가 실제로 ResNet에서
that we discussed in ResNets, where
논의한 아이디어와
you have these skip connections, where the value is just
매우 관련이 있다는 것입니다. 여기서 스킵
copied over and added later in the layer block.
연결이 있어 값이 복사되어 나중에 레이어 블록에서 추가됩니다.
So you have multiple in ResNets.
그래서 ResNet에서는 여러 개가 있습니다.
You have multiple of these convolution layers stacked
여러 개의 합성곱 층이 함께
together, and then you add skip connections where the value just
쌓여 있고, 여기서 값이 더해지는 스킵
gets added here.
연결을 추가합니다.
And you can think of this in a similar light
LSTM에 대해서도 비슷한 관점에서
for LSTMs, how it's skipping over some of these layers
생각할 수 있으며, 이는 일부 층을
and it helps improve as you get in this case,
건너뛰는 방식으로 모델의 깊이가 매우
instead of very large depth of the model.
크지 않도록 도와줍니다.
It's very long sequences of time steps.
매우 긴 시간 단계의 시퀀스입니다.
So this is parallel, but it's a little different
이것은 병렬적이지만,
because one is the number of layers
한쪽은 층의 수이고
and the other is the number of time steps.
다른 쪽은 시간 단계의 수입니다.
OK, I think the final slide for today's lecture
오늘 강의의 마지막 슬라이드는 RNN이 지난
is just a little tie-in for how these RNNs have made
1~2년 동안 다시 주목받고 있다는 점을 간단히 연결하는
a bit of a resurgence in the last year or two,
것입니다. 재미있는 점은, 만약
which is funny, because I think if we taught the course maybe
우리가 1~2년 전에 이 과정을 가르쳤다면
a year or two ago, I would have been much more willing to want
RNN을 완전히 배제하고 싶었을
to cut RNNs entirely.
것입니다.
But there are actually a lot of nice advantages they have.
하지만 실제로 그들이 가진 많은 장점이 있습니다.
So the main one is this unlimited context length.
주요 장점은 무제한의 컨텍스트 길이입니다.
So one of the main issues with transformers
트랜스포머의 주요 문제 중 하나는 제한된 컨텍스트
is they have a limited context length, as people are really
길이를 가지고 있다는 것입니다. 사람들이 이 모델들이
pushing the boundaries for what these models are capable of.
할 수 있는 것의 경계를 정말로 밀어붙이고 있습니다.
This context length is becoming more and more of an issue.
이 컨텍스트 길이는 점점 더 문제가 되고 있습니다.
So there have been various workarounds in the transformer
트랜스포머 공간에서 다양한 우회 방법이
space.
있었습니다.
People do things like rope and some other techniques
사람들은 로프와 같은 기술을
to try to extend the context length,
사용하여 컨텍스트 길이를
but it's a pretty significant limitation of the model.
늘리려고 하지만, 이는 모델의 상당한 제한입니다.
The other thing is that during inference for RNNs,
RNN의 추론 중에는 계산이 시퀀스 길이에 따라
the compute scales linearly with the sequence length
선형적으로 확장되며, 훈련 중에도
or during training to, but basically,
마찬가지입니다. 기본적으로
as you add more and more steps to your sequence,
시퀀스에 더 많은 단계를 추가할수록 같은
you just need to recompute the same operation over and over
작업을 반복해서 재계산해야
again.
합니다.
So there's no operation that looks across the entire input
트랜스포머와 같은 전체 입력
sequence like you have for transformers.
시퀀스를 가로지르는 작업은 없습니다.
So these are really big advantages,
이것들은 정말 큰 장점이며,
and there have been a couple of papers.
몇 가지 논문이 있습니다.
So to shout out a few, there's this RWKV model.
몇 가지를 언급하자면, RWKV 모델이 있습니다.
You can check out arXiv link here,
여기 arXiv 링크를
and also Mamba are both mainly highlighting
확인할 수 있으며, Mamba도 주로 선형 시간 시퀀스
this idea of we're able to achieve linear time sequence
모델링을 달성할 수 있다는 아이디어를
modeling.
강조합니다.
So as you scale up your input sequence,
입력 시퀀스를 확장할수록
the compute also scales linearly as opposed to quadratically
계산도 트랜스포머와 달리 선형적으로
with transformers.
확장됩니다.
And so it's better for long context problems sometimes.
그래서 때때로 긴 컨텍스트 문제에 더 좋습니다.
In terms of compute it works better,
계산 측면에서 더 잘 작동하며, 이러한
and it has these main advantages.
주요 장점이 있습니다.
So people try to get the best of both worlds,
사람들은 두 세계의 장점을 모두 얻으려고
and there's been a lot of research in this area.
노력하며, 이 분야에서 많은 연구가 진행되고 있습니다.
How can you get the performance of transformers
트랜스포머의 성능을 RNN의
with the scaling of RNNs?
확장성과 어떻게 결합할 수 있을까요?
OK, so that's all for today in class.
오늘 수업은 여기까지입니다.
We basically talked about how, there's a lot of different ways
우리는 기본적으로 RNN으로 아키텍처를 설계할 수
you can design architectures with RNNs.
있는 다양한 방법에 대해 이야기했습니다.
Vanilla RNNs are simple, but they don't work that well.
바닐라 RNN은 간단하지만 잘 작동하지 않습니다.
And there's been more complex variants
정보를 선택적으로
that people have proposed that introduce ways to selectively
전달하는 방법을 도입한 더 복잡한
pass information.
변형들이 제안되었습니다.
This backward flow of gradients in RNNs
RNN에서의 그래디언트의 역흐름은
can either explode or vanish, depending on the activation
사용하는 활성화 함수나 가중치
function you use, or what is the properties of your weight
행렬의 특성에 따라 폭발하거나 사라질 수
matrix.
있습니다.
So you often need this back propagation through time
그래서 실제로 그래디언트를 계산하기 위해
to actually compute the gradient as well.
시간에 따른 역전파가 필요합니다.
And then finally, basically these better architectures
마지막으로, 이러한 더 나은 아키텍처는 현재
are a hot topic of research right now, as well
뜨거운 연구 주제이며, 시퀀스를 다루는
as just generally new paradigms for reasoning over sequences.
새로운 패러다임에 대한 일반적인 관심도 있습니다.
So yeah, I think that's it for today.
그래서 오늘은 여기까지입니다.
Next time we'll talk about attention and transformers.
다음 시간에는 주의(attention)와 트랜스포머에 대해 이야기하겠습니다.